<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Didascalocophus, or, The deaf and dumb mans tutor to which is added a discourse of the nature and number of double consonants, both which tracts being the first (for what the author knows) that have been published upon either of the subjects / by Geo. Dalgarno.</title>
            <author>Dalgarno, George, 1626?-1687.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 160 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 74 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35856</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D129</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11949</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12254476</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12254476</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57291</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35856)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57291)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 888:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Didascalocophus, or, The deaf and dumb mans tutor to which is added a discourse of the nature and number of double consonants, both which tracts being the first (for what the author knows) that have been published upon either of the subjects / by Geo. Dalgarno.</title>
                  <author>Dalgarno, George, 1626?-1687.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 136 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Deaf --  Education --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Speech --  Study and teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57291:1"/>
            <p>DIDASCALOCOPHUS Or The Deaf and Dumb mans Tutor, <hi>To which is added</hi> A Diſcourſe of the Nature and number of Double Conſonants. Both which Tracts being the firſt (for what the Author knows) that have been publiſhed upon either of the Subjects. By <hi>GEO. DALGARNO.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of the University of Oxford, featuring the Sheldonian Theatre</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at the THEATER in OXFORD, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:57291:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>TIMO. HALTON</hi> Vice-Cancel <hi>Oxon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Read Didaſcalocophus for <hi>Cheiralogy,</hi> p. 96. l. 7. and p. 104. l. 22. Read uſe for <hi>uſe,</hi> p. 27. l. 1. Read moſt for <hi>leaſt.</hi> p. 128. l. 8.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:57291:2"/>
            <head>THE INTRODUCTION, With a KEY <hi>to the following diſcourſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ABOUT <hi>20</hi> years agoe, I publiſhed, <hi>Latiali</hi> but <hi>rudi Minerva,</hi> a Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pſis of a Philoſophical Grammar and Lexicon; thereby ſhewing a way to remedy the difficulties and abſurdities which all languages are clogg'd with ever ſince the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or rather ſince the fall; by cutting off all Redundancy, rectifying all Anomoly, taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all Ambiguity and Aequivocation, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the Primitives to a few number, and even thoſe not to be of a meer arbitrary, but a ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Inſtitution; enlarging the bounds of deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and Compoſition, for the cauſe both of <hi>Copia</hi> and <hi>Emphaſis.</hi> In a word, deſigning not only to remedie the confuſion of Languages, by giving a much more eaſie medium of communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation then any yet known; but alſo to cure even Philoſophy it ſelf of the diſeaſe of Sophiſms, and
<pb facs="tcp:57291:3"/>Logomachies; as alſo to provide her with more wieldy and mannageable. Inſtruments of opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for defining, dividing, demonſtrating, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What entertainment this deſign may meet with in following ages, I am not ſolicitous to know; but that it has met with ſo little in this preſent age, I could give ſeveral good reaſons, which at preſent I forbear; intending, if God bleſs one with life, health, and leiſure to do this in a more proper place. To me 'tis enough to have the Teſtimony of ſome of the learned men of this preſent age
<note n="*" place="margin">Dr. Seth Wind <hi>now Lord Biſhop of</hi> Sarum, Dr. John Wilkins <hi>late Lord Biſhop of</hi> Cheſter, Dr. John Wallis, Dr. William Dittingham.</note> who are beſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to judge in things of this nature, that I have there diſcovered a ſecret of Art, which by the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men of former ages, has been reckoned among the Deſiderate of Learning: To which I may add, that this diſcovery is made from more ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, eaſy, and practicable principles, than e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they imagined to be poſſible.</p>
            <p>To this treatiſe I gave the title of <hi>Ars Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnorum,</hi> which in compliance with the Dialect of the preſent Scene, I may properly enough
<pb facs="tcp:57291:3"/>change to <hi>Sematology.</hi> This ſoon after be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a fruitful Mother of two Siſter-Germans, <hi>Didaſcalocophus,</hi> and a <hi>Diſcourſe of double Conſonants;</hi> which having lyen as twins in the womb for many years, at laſt two ſevere fits of ſickneſs did midwive them into the world, the latter here in order being <hi>Senior</hi> to the other by the ſpace of full <hi>7</hi> years.</p>
            <p>That the argument I have in hand is worthy to be treated of, will readily be confeſſed by <hi>all;</hi> but how worthily I have handled it muſt be judged by a <hi>few,</hi> to whoſe candor (paſſing by all apologies) I freely ſubmit. The former treatiſe of <hi>Sematology</hi> had the Univerſality of all mankind for its object, but had nothing to recommend it but conveniency; This of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſcalocophus,</hi> is reſtrained (at leaſt in its moſt proper ends and principal effects) to a ſmall number of mankind; but comes recommended with the ſtrongeſt arguments of Charity and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity. But at preſent I will diſmiſs the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and betake my ſelf to put the Daughter in a proper dreſs for the following Scene of action.</p>
            <p>The Soul of Man in this ſtate of union depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:57291:4"/>in its operations upon the bodily Organs; when theſe are vitiated it muſt needs follow, that the Soul it ſelf is ſo far affected, as at leaſt to be hindred in her external functions. Being therefore to treat of a way to cure a weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that follows humane nature, equally affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both: I will leave it to the skilful Phyſician, to diſcourſe of the cauſes and cure of the Diſeaſe, as it concerns the Body, and will apply my ſelf to conſider of the means, to cure the better part of the Man, which is the proper work of a Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marian.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the ſubject I have in hand is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and more particularly one branch of it, which for what I know, has been hitherto <hi>ex profeſſo</hi> treated of by no Author: I will firſt mention all the ſeveral wayes of Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, whereby the Soul either doth, or may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xert her powers: In doing of which I will be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged to take the liberty of coyning ſome new words of Art, which hereafter I will explain.</p>
            <p>It is true that all the Senſes are Intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers to the Soul leſs or more; for tho they have their diſtinct limits, and proper Objects aſſigned them by nature; yet ſhe is able to uſe their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb facs="tcp:57291:4"/>even in the moſt abſtracted Notions, and Arbitrary inſtitution: But with this difference, that Nature ſeems to have fitted two, <hi>Hearing</hi> and <hi>Seeing,</hi> more particularly for her ſervice; And other two <hi>Taſting</hi> and <hi>Smelling,</hi> more groſs and material, for her dull and heavy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort the Body: whereas the fifth of <hi>Touching</hi> is of a midle nature, and in a manner equally fitted for the ſervice of both, as will appear in the progreſs of the following diſcourſe. Wherefore being here to ſpeak of the Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of arbitrary Signs, impreſt by the Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Soule (and by it alone) upon the Objects of the Senſes, moſt fitted for that uſe: I will take notice of the moſt uſual, or at leaſt of the moſt eaſy and practicable wayes of Interpretation which either are, or may be.</p>
            <p>Here reflecting upon <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I expected both his help and Authority, in Analyſing the ſeveral kinds of Interpretation: But finding little or nothing to this purpoſe in him, neither indeed in any other Author of old or new Philoſophy (as wee now diſtinguiſh) that I have happened to look in, I was forced to adventure upon the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
<pb facs="tcp:57291:5"/>Analyſis, for clearing my way, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abling me to diſcourſe the more diſtinctly on the Subject Argument.</p>
            <p>Interpretation then in its largeſt ſenſe, is <hi>an act of cognitive power, expreſſing the inward motions, by outward and ſenſible Signs:</hi> Of this there are three kindes, <hi>1.</hi> Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural, <hi>2.</hi> Natural, <hi>3.</hi> Artificial or Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutional; to which I give the names of Chre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matology, Phyſiology, and Sematology. Chre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matology, is when Almighty God reveals his will by extraordinary means, as dreams, viſions, apparitions <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and this in the diviſion of Arts falls under Divinity. Phyſiology is when the internal paſſions, are expreſſed by ſuch external Signs, as have a natural connexion by way of cauſe and effect with the paſſion they diſcover; as laughing, weeping, frowning, &amp;c. And this way of Interpretation being common to the Brute with Man, belongs to Natural Philoſophy: And becauſe this goes not far enough, to ſerve the Rational Soul, therefore Man has invented Sematology; that is, an Art of impreſſing the conceits of the mind upon ſenſible and material Objects, which have not the leaſt ſhadow of affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb facs="tcp:57291:5"/>to the images of the things they carry impreſt upon them. And this is Interpretation, in the ſtricteſt and moſt proper ſenſe; and to reduce this wonderful effect of Reaſon to ſuch Rules of Art as the nature of it requires, is the proper Subject of <hi>Ars Signorunt;</hi> which according to the commonly recieved diſtribution of Arts, is nothing elſe but a Rational Grammar.</p>
            <p>Sematology then being a General name for all Interpretation by Arbitrary Signs, or (to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the moſt uſual aims of Art) <hi>voces ex in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituto;</hi> to any of the Senſes; It may from the three Senſes of Hearing, Seeing, and Touching, whoſe ſervice the Soul doth chiefly make uſe of in Interpretation, be divided into Pneumatology; Schematology, and Haptology.</p>
            <p>Pneumatology, (or if any think Ethology more proper) is Interpretation by Sounds con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veied thro the Ear; Schematology by Figures to the Eye; and Haptology by a mutual contact, skin to skin. Pneumatology again is divided into Gloſſology and Aulology: Gloſſology is a term proper enough for Interpretation by the Tongue, which is the firſt, and moſt common Organ of Interpretation at leaſt in Society, and
<pb facs="tcp:57291:6"/>face to face; for Man in theſe circumſtances</p>
            <q>—<hi>effert animi motus interprete Lingua.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Aulology ſo ſtyled by an eaſy Trope, interprets by a Muſical Inſtrument; which is fully capable of as much, and manifeſt diſtinction as the Tongue, but not ſo natural and ready an Organ.</p>
            <p>Schematology is divided into Typology or Grammatology, and Cheirology or Dactylology. By Typology or Grammatology, I underſtand the impreſſing of permanent Figures upon ſolid and conſiſting matter, which may be done two wayes; either by the Pen and Hand, or by the impreſſion of Stamps prepared for that uſe; which makes only an accidental difference between Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tology and Typology. Cheirology or Dactylolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, as the words import, is Interpretation by the tranſient motions of the Fingers; which of all other wayes of Interpretation comes neareſt to that of the Tongue. Haptology admitting of no Medium, nor diſtinction of Act and Object, but being body to body, doth therefore admitt of no ſubdiviſion. Tho I will not warrant all theſe Terms from Acyrology; yet I am ſure that they will both ſave me the labour of Periphraſis, and alſo from uſing words leſs proper.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:57291:6"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:57291:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57291:7"/>
            <head>CHAP. I. <hi>A Deaf man as capable of underſtanding and expreſſing a Language, as a Blind.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THO the Soul of man come into the world, <hi>Tabula Raſa;</hi> yet is it withal, <hi>Tabula Cerata;</hi> capable thro ſtudy and diſcipline, of having ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fair, and goodly images, ſtampt upon it. This capacity is actuated, by the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of bodily Organs. The Organs of the Body, ſerving the Soul in exerting her powers, in this ſtate of union are four; the Eye and the Ear; the Hand and the Tongue: the firſt pair fitted for taking in, the other for giving out; Both the one and the other, equally neceſſary for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, and ſociety.</p>
            <p>That the Ear and the Tongue alone, ſecluding the other two, can perfect a man in knowledge (excepting of ſome few things which are the proper Objects of ſeeing) and enable him to expreſs what he knows in Vocal Signs, or a Language
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:57291:8"/>ſpoken, is known by daily experience in blind people. That an equal degree of knowledge is attainable by the Eye, and expreſſible by the Hand in Characters, or a Language written, is no leſs evident in the Theory, for the reaſons following.</p>
            <p>All ſigns, both vocal, and written, are equally arbitrary and <hi>ex inſtituto.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any reaſon in Nature, why the mind ſhould more eaſily apprehend, the images of things impreſt upon Sounds, than upon Characters; when there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing either natural, or Symbolical, in the one or the other.</p>
            <p>Therefore that blind people ſhould come ſooner to ſpeak, and underſtand, than Dumb perſons to write, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, is not, becauſe there is any more diſcerning faculty in the Ear, than in the Eye; nor from the Nature of Sounds and Characters, that the one ſhould have a greater fitneſs then the other to conveigh thoſe Notions impreſt upon them, thro the reſpective doors of the Senſes into the Soul; neither that pronounciation of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulate words is ſooner, or, more eaſily learned, then written Characters; neither
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57291:8"/>yet, that the Ear is quicker in perceiving its object then the Eye: But it is from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther accidental cauſes, and circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which give the Ear many conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able advantages, in the matter of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, above the Eye. And yet, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in this particular, the Eye wants not its own priviledges; which if rightly uſed, may perhaps outweigh the advantages on the other ſide. For illuſtrating this, I will compare a Deaf man with a Blind. 1. The blind man goes to School in his cradle; this ſo early care is not taken of the Deaf. 2. The blind man is ſtill learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from all that are about him; For e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very body he converſes with, is a Tutor, and every word he hears, is a lecture to him; by which he either learns what he knew not, or confirms what he had. The Deaf man not being capable of this way of diſcipline, has no teacher at all: and tho neceſſity may put him upon contriving, &amp; uſing a few ſigns; yet thoſe have no affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to the Language by which they that are about him do converſe amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and therefore are of little uſe to him. 3. The Blind man goes thro the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57291:9"/>diſcipline of Language in the beſt of his time, Childhood, and under the beſt of Teachers, women and children: The Deaf man is deprived of both theſe op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities. 4. The blind man learns his Language by the by, and <hi>aliud agens;</hi> the Deaf cannot attain a language without inſtruction, and the expence of much time and pains. 5. The deaf man is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to the circumſtances of light, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, poſture of body, both in himſelf, and him he communicates with: the blind man is free from theſe ſtreightning cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, all the advantages the Ear has above the eye, may be ſummed up in theſe two. Firſt, more opportunities of time; ſecondly, quicker diſpatch, or doing more work in leſs time: Both which may be in a great meaſure remedied by skill and care; by which if there were a timely applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made to Deaf perſons, I conceive they might be more improved in knowledge; and ſo their condition be much more happy than that of the blind: which will appear by the following advantages that the Deaf man has above the Blind.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:57291:9"/>
            <p>Firſt, the Deaf man has greater advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of acquiring Real knowledge, than the blind; becauſe the Eye has greater variety of objects then the Ear. 2. The Deaf man has a greater certainty of that knowledge he attains by the Eye, than the Blind can have of that he receives by the Ear; for <hi>Pluris eſt oculatus teſtis unus, quam auriti decem.</hi> 3. As he has the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the other in the knowledge of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; ſo alſo he exceeds him much, in Speaking and Reading the Language of Nature. For beſides reading the Glory, and wiſdom of God, in the book of the Creation; he is able alſo to read much of the minds of men, in the Book of their Countenance; which, ſeconded with the poſtures, geſtures, actions of the whole body; more particularly, the indications of the hands, feet, fingers, and other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances; laies open much of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide to him: And he, by the ſame Dumb eloquence is able to notifie his deſires to others. Of which way of communication, the blind mans condition renders him wholly uncapable. So that the one is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to prove himſelf a man, in any ſociety
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57291:10"/>of Mankind, all the world over: The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, take him from the company of his country-men, has little elſe left him wherewith to difference himſelf from a brute, but the childiſh Rhetorick of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocritus,</hi> and <hi>Heraclitus.</hi> But fourthly, to come cloſer to our purpoſe with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon. The Deaf man learns a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage by Art, and exerciſing his rational faculties; the Blind man learns by Rote; ſo that he gets a language and he himſelf knows not how. There is therefore as great difference in the point of language between a Deaf and a Blind man (ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing both to have made an equal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs,) as between one bred in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, and a Clown that knows not a letter. Fifthly, tho the Blind man have the ſtart of the Deaf, yet the deaf man will be too hard for him at the long run: For he, after he has once got a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency of language, will be able to help himſelf, and direct his own courſe in the further purſuit of all Real knowledge. On the contrary, the blind man who in learning a language needed no particular Guide, becauſe every body was his Guide;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57291:10"/>now he is at a ſtand, and cannot ſo much as advance one ſtep, without one to lead him. Sixthly, the Deaf man has this great advantage above the Blind, which weighs heavier then all that can be laid in the Scales againſt it: That he is able to write down his notions, and reflect upon them as often as he will. And now the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of having much time for ſtudy, and doing much work in little time is as much the Deaf mans, as at firſt ſetting out it was the Blind mans. Seventhly, in the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfetation of language the Deaf man will ſooner be impregnate with a 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>, or 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>, language then the Blind; inſomuch as one language learned by ſtudy and Art, is a greater ſtep to facilitate the learning of another, then the mother Tongue which comes by meer uſe and Rote.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:57291:11"/>
            <head>CHAP. II. <hi>A Deaf man capable of as Early Inſtruction in a language as a Blind.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TAking it for granted, That Deaf peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are equal, in the faculties of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, and memory, not only to the Blind; but even to thoſe that have all their ſenſes: and having formerly ſhewn; that theſe faculties can as eaſily receive, and retain, the Images of things, by the conveiance of Figures, thro the Eye, as of Sounds thro the Ear: It will follow, That the Deaf man is, not only, as capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; but alſo, as ſoon capable of Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in Letters, as the blind man. And if we compare them, as to their intrinſick powers, has the advantage of him too; inſomuch as he has a more diſtinct and perfect perception, of external Objects, then the other. For the Blind man has no certain knowledge of things without him; but what he receives, from the informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the groſs ſenſe of Feeling; which,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57291:11"/>tho it be a ſure intelligencer; yet is its in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence very ſcanty: For what he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives by the Ear, is but a ſecond-hand knowledge, depending upon teſtimony, and the credit of others. So that the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages I gave the blind man, at firſt ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out, are not in his own faculties, but from extrinſick and adventitious helps.</p>
            <p>Therefore I conceive, there might be ſuccesful addreſſes made to a Dumb child, even in his cradle; when he begins —<hi>riſu cognoſcere matrem:</hi> if the Mother, or, Nurſe had but as nimble a hand, as commonly they have a Tongue. For inſtance, I doubt not but the words, <hi>hand, foot, dog, cat, hat,</hi> &amp;c. written fair, and as often pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the Deaf childs Eye, pointing from the words to the Things and <hi>vice verſa;</hi> as the blind child hears them ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, would be known, and remembred aſſoon by the one, as the other. And as I think the Eye to be as docile, as the Ear; ſo neither ſee I any reaſon, but the Hand might be made as tractable an Organ, as the Tongue; and aſſoon brought to form, if not fair, at leaſt legible Characters, as
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57291:12"/>the tongue to imitate, and Echo back, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulate Sounds.</p>
            <p>Here it may be doubted; whether it were more adviſable, to train up the deaf child in Typology, or Dactylology. For the firſt, it may be ſaid, That tho the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution is equally arbitrary in both, and therefore equally eaſy to the learner: yet, writing is permanent, and therefore gives the young Scholar time to contemplate, and ſo makes the deeper impreſſion: whereas, pointing to the fingers is tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſient, and gone before it can be appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended. This made me at firſt incline more to writing: But upon further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, I judge the other way much more expedient. For tho it cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, but the permanency of the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters is in it ſelf an advantage, if well improved; yet, tranſient motions, if of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten repeated, make as great an impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon the memory, as fixt and immov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able objects. A clear proof of this we have from young ones learning to underſtand a Language, from the Tranſient moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the tongue: and which is yet more difficult; to imitate the ſame tranſient
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57291:12"/>motions; where, neither can the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions be ſo manifeſt, nor the formati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo eaſy, as in the Hand-language. Which, as it confirms me; That pointing to the Hand, would be the better way of teaching, ſo it makes me think: That if cloſely followed, it might be eaſier at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, by young ones, then ſpeaking; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as the motions of the Hand, are much more eaſy then thoſe of the tongue.</p>
            <p>If here it ſhould be objected; That words written are more diſtinct, and eaſy to be apprehended; for tho conſiſting of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral diſtinct letters; yet being joyned, they paſs in this rude diſcipline, for one indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual Sign, for our Scholar is ſuppoſed as yet, to underſtand nothing of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of letters: whereas in pointing to the Fingers; The diſtinct motions to make up a word, will be more manifeſt; and ſo will be a hinderance to the Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars weak intention, to apprehend that, which is repreſented by many touches ſo diſtinctly, under the Notion of one word.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer. If we compare the action of writing, with pointing to the Fingers, this is much more ſimple then
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57291:13"/>that; and therefore leſs amuſing. But ſecondly, if we compare words written with pointing; this is ſtill not only more ſimple, and therefore more eaſily appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended; But alſo it is as eaſy to repreſent a word as one <hi>Compoſitum</hi> with a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed action of the Hand, tho there be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſtinct pointings, as to make One Word by an aggregate of many diſtinct letters. Add to this, that pointing to the Hand is capable of more Emphaſis; for frequent repetition accompanied with ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnificant geſtures, will come near to the way of teaching <hi>viva voce,</hi> which incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates more then the beholding of a ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing object. But here there is need of cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; That we follow the conduct of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; That is, to begin with Words moſt ſimple and eaſy. For we ſee that young children when they begin to ſpeak are not able to pronounce long words, nor yet all letters. But here the only care to be taken is, to chuſe ſhort words; for all let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are equally eaſy. Now before I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed I think it will be very proper to add ſome thing of the eaſineſs of the whole Task; both to remove prejudices in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57291:13"/>and more particularly to encourage the careful Mother the more cheerfully to undertake it.</p>
            <p>There are many mothers who (to their great praiſe) do teach their children to Read, even almoſt before they can ſpeak. And yet (I hope) it will appear from the following conſiderations; That to read and write upon the Fingers, is much ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier to the learner, than to read and write in Books; there being many difficulties in the one, which are avoided in the other. For, 1. in reading, ſingle letters muſt be learned; which are very remote, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted from ſenſe, as being but parts of a Signs Sign, e. g. H. is the 4th part of the word <hi>Hand,</hi> which word written is a ſign of the vocal ſound, the vocal ſound is the immediate ſign of the thing it ſelf. 2. Next to this difficulty is the learning to name the ſame letters in the preciſe abſtracted notion of them <hi>a, b, c, d,</hi> &amp;c. without bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing names to them from other things; contrary to what the firſt fathers of let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters have taught us, as appears by their naming the ſimple elements <hi>Aleph, Beth, Gimel, Daleth,</hi> &amp;c. And here by the by I
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57291:14"/>cannot but obſerve; That we <hi>Europeans</hi> have been ſo dull Sholars, as not to take out the leſſon: Yea our wiſe Maſters the Grecians in this particular, are the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Dunces of the reſt; For others have been truants and taken out no leſſon; and they have taken it out falſe. For they have named them by Barbarous and inſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant words corrupted from the Hebrew; which is worſe then to name them by their own powers alone. Which halluci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of theirs has a remarkable provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in it; For thereby they have given a convincing proof, and openly confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed (tho they neither deſigned, nor own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any ſuch thing) that the Doctors of <hi>Athens</hi> have learned their a b c at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel.</hi> And here amongſt our ſelves and neighbouring Nations, it is obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that in this point of diſcipline, our Dames are wiſer than our Doctors: for they find a neceſſity of bringing home theſe abſtracted notions to young ones ſenſes, by borrowing names from known and familiar things. But if there were one way of naming the ſimple Elements agreed upon, and this put in all Primers
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57291:14"/>and Horn-books, it would not only be of good uſe to children and unskilful Dames; but alſo the thing being celebrated would give occaſion to ingenious alluſions and Metaphors, an inſtance whereof we have in A and Ω in the Greek. But to return to our purpoſe. A third difficulty in read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is true pronounciation of the ſimple letters. And 4. joyning them in ſyllables is yet more difficult; the ſingle letters of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times either quite looſing, or, chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their powers. And <hi>5.</hi> the dividing ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lables a right, and joyning them to make words. All which are ſuch difficulties that one may juſtly wonder how young ones come to get over them: And how late, and with how great pains they are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by ſome, I appeal to thoſe that know what belongs to the breeding of youth. Now the Deaf child under his Mothers tuition, paſſes ſecurely by all theſe Rocks and Quick-ſands. The diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of letters, their names, their powers, their order, the giving them true ſhape or figure (which anſwers to others pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing true,) the dividing words into Syllables, and of them again making
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57291:15"/>words, to which may be added Tone, and Accent. None of theſe puzling niceties hinder his progreſs. All the teacher has to do, is, to go with one continued mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion over all the points that make up the word, pointing withal to the things. And at firſt it will be convenient to ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate the young Scholar with words of few letters. and a near affinity; as, <hi>Hat, Cat, Hog, Dog, Hand, Sand.</hi> It is true, after he has paſt the diſcipline of the Nurſery, and comes to learn Grammatically, then he muſt begin to learn to know letters writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, by their figure, number, and order. But the reſt of the difficulties I have but now mentioned, are proper to the Ear, and therefore do not concern him.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the advantages the Blind man hath over the Deaf, are more conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derably ſuch, in the time of childhood; It cannot be denied, but the blind child, is in a greater capacity of learning the Mother-Tongue then the Deaf: yet ſo, as skill and care might advance the Deaf child in a vocabulary of the names of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Objects, much above what the other can be ſuppoſed to get from the common
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57291:15"/>uſe of the Mother-Tongue. For the one is ſtill running the ſame round, in a narrow circle, hearing the ſame words redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly: the other might be in a conſtant progreſſive motion.</p>
            <p>And tho I perſwade my ſelf, that ſome time or other, there may be a mother found, who by her own care, and ſuch directions as I am treating of, will lay a good foundation of Language in her Deaf child, even in the firſt ſtage of his Minority; yet ſeeing this is like to be but <hi>rara avis,</hi> I will advance our blind and deaf Scholars to a higher Form, and place them under a ſeverer diſcipline then that of the Nurſery; which I ſuppoſe none will deny them now able to bear: for I will ſuppoſe them entred in the 7th year of their age. Together then with this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality of age, let us ſuppoſe them every other way equal, in their natural parts, both faculties and inclinations, under Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors equally both skilful and careful: And to make their capacities every way equal; the Deaf boy to write as fair and quick a hand, as can be expected from that age. In theſe circumſtances, they are
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57291:16"/>both of them to begin to learn a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage: the blind boy Latin, the deaf boy his Mothers Tongue.</p>
            <p>The caſe being thus ſtated, It is my own opinion, that the Deaf boy would come to read &amp; write the Mother-Tongue both much better and ſooner then the blind boy to underſtand and ſpeak the Latin. For reaſons of my ſo thinking, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide what may be gathered from chap. 1. I will here carry on the compariſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the blind boy and the deaf in ſome particulars coming cloſer to our preſent caſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Blind boy has the advantage of knowing a language already, which is a great help to the learning any ſecond language. For tho there be no affinity between the words of ſome languages; yet there is ſomething of a Natural and Univerſal Grammar runs thro all Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, wherein all agree. This contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts not what I have ſaid to the deaf mans advantage Chap. 1. Num. 6. Becauſe there the blind and deaf are ſuppoſed both to underſtand the Mother-Tongue when they begin to learn a ſecond lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57291:16"/>Here the deaf is ſuppoſed to have no language, and the blind to have the Mother-Tongue; which tho by him learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, not by Rule, but by Rote; yet is it an advantage over him that has none.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Beſide this notion of Natural and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Grammar, which the blindboy hath got with the Mother-Tongue; he not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to learn Words for Things, but Words for Words; and it falling out ſo, that often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times there is a great affinity between the words to be learned, and the words for which they are to be learned; this makes that he learns with leſs pains then the deaf boy, who learning words for Things, it can never happen, that a combination of Alphabetical Characters making up a word, ſhould have any affinity to, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of the thing for which it is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Onomatopoeia is a great help to the blind Scholar, for Example, <hi>grunnitus, hinnitus, rugitus, ululatus,</hi> &amp;c. are eaſier to be learned by the blind man, then the deaf; becauſe as they paſs in Sounds thro the Ear, they are of a mixt Inſtitution, partly Natural, partly Arbitrary; But
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57291:17"/>theſe ſame words written in Characters are of a meer arbitrary Inſtitution, whether they be conſidered with relation to the immediate, or mediate <hi>Signatum.</hi> So that our dumb Scholar has nothing to truſt to, but diligence and ſtrength of memory: Reaſon can do him no ſervice at all, at leaſt ſo far as either Primitive words, or words of an irregular inflexion from them extend; which make up the body of all languages. Neither can fancy help him much, which oftentimes is of great uſe by working a connexion between a ſtrange and a known word, becauſe as yet we ſuppoſe moſt words to be ſtrangers to him.</p>
            <p>The reaſon of this difference between words ſpoken and written is. Becauſe ſpeaking being before writing, has more of Nature and leſs of Art in it. For all languages guided by the inſtinct of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, have more or leſs of Onomatopoeia in them, and I think our <hi>Engliſh</hi> as much as any: For beſide the naming the voices of Animals, and ſome other Muſical Sounds, which for the moſt part is done by this Figure in other languages, we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57291:17"/>it often to more obſcure, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinct ſounds. Take for example, <hi>waſh, daſh, plaſh, flaſh, claſh, haſh, laſh, ſlaſh, traſh, gaſh,</hi> &amp;c. So <hi>grumble, tumble, crum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, jumble, fumble, ſtumble, humble, mum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> &amp;c. of which kind of words, The Learned and my worthy friend Dr <hi>Wallis</hi> has given a good account in his <hi>Engliſh</hi> Grammar. In all theſe and ſuch like words there is ſomething Symboliz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Analogous to the notions of the things; which makes them both more Emphatic, and eaſy to the memory. But in words literally written, and of a meer arbitrary Inſtitution, there can be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Symbolical. But to draw ſomething out of this digreſſion to our preſent ſtated caſe. Tho Onomatopoeia gives our blind Scholar ſome advantage over his Deaf Schoolfellow; yet is it ſhort of what it would be if he were learning <hi>Engliſh.</hi> This is all that at preſent comes into my thoughts to ſay for maintaining the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox of <hi>a blind guide.</hi> I will now offer my reaſons for giving him the precedency, that has two Eyes open in his head, which ſeems to be the more plauſible opinion.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:57291:18"/>
            <p n="1">1. The Deaf mans mind is like clean pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and therefore takes the impreſſion the more eaſily, fair and diſtinct: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the ſcriblings and blottings upon the Table of the Blind mans memory, as they leave little room for new impreſſions, ſo they breed confuſion, and makes him rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to miſtake, when he comes to read them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Words laid up in the deaf Boyes me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, are like Characters engraven in Steel or Marble: The blind boyes words are but chalked out, or, <hi>nigro carbone No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tata,</hi> and therefore eaſily defaced. For the deaf boy having but one word for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing he knows, is therefore obliged to reflect upon it, as often as he has occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to think, or ſpeak of the thing it ſelf: And it is this frequency of recognizing words, and uſing them upon all occaſions that makes a man maſter of a Language: Whereas the blind boy having two words for one thing, the one an intimate and old acquaintance, even a <hi>teneris unguicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> the other a ſtranger to him; upon all occaſions he loves to converſe with his old crony, and keeps at a diſtance from
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57291:18"/>the ſtranger; unleſs it be at ſet times, when force or fear commands his attendance. So that this conſideration alone (ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if it be ſeconded with the care and diligence of thoſe that are about him, in forbearing all other Signs with him but letters) may ſeem to outweigh all that can be ſaid for the blind Boy.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The deaf boy can conn a leſſon by himſelf, for <hi>litera ſcripta manet;</hi> The Blind boy can do nothing without one prompting him for <hi>vox perit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, I think none will deny but that it ſtands with reaſon, That a deaf Scholar muſt be exact in Orthography. But for the blind I know it by experience, that it will be a hard matter to make him ſpel true.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:57291:19"/>
            <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of a Deaf mans Capacity to ſpeak.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THAT a Deaf man may be taught to ſpeak, is no more a doubt to me, then that a Blind man may be taught to write: Both which I think not only poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but alſo not very difficult; I will carry on the compariſon in ſeveral parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars. Firſt, both have the reſpective Organs, the Tongue, and the Hand, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually entire, and in a capacity to act. 2. Both are equally deſtitute of their proper guids, the Ey, and the Ear, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them in acting: and therefore, 3. both muſt be equally obliged to the ſenſe of of Feeling for direction.</p>
            <p>And yet ſo Magiſterial are the Senſes of Hearing, and Seeing; that tho the Senſe of Feeling alone may guide the Tongue, and Hand, in ſpeaking, and writing, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a habit is acquired yet for introducing this habit, directions from the Eye, and Ear are neceſſary. And which is obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:57291:19"/>in this point of diſcipline: The eye and ear ſeem to act out of their own Sphere, and to exchange their ſtations, and powers; for the Blind man learns to write by the Ear, and the Deaf man to ſpeak by the Eye: From which to infer that community of Senſes, which ſome Philoſophers, and Phyſicians ſpeak of, I think would be abſurd; the external ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ſtill remaining diſtinct: But the true inference from this will be. That the ſoul can exert her powers, by the miniſtry of any of the Senſes. And therefore when ſhe is deprived of her principal Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, the eye, and the ear; then ſhe muſt be contented with the ſervice of her Lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queys, and Scullions, the other Senſes; which are no leſs true and faithful to their Miſtreſs, then the eye, and the ear; but not ſo quick for diſpatch.</p>
            <p>But to go on with the compariſon. 4. It will be hard to teach the deaf man to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve tone, accent, and Emphaſis in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; ſo will it be as hard to bring the blind man to write a fair hand, or diverſe hands, yet the one may ſpeak ſo as to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and the other write ſo as what he
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:57291:20"/>writes may be read. 5. As there may be more ſimple, and therefore more eaſy Characters to be written, contrived for the uſe of the blind man; So may there ſounds of an eaſier pronounciation than any in common uſe, be invented for the uſe of the Deaf, 6. They are equally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable the one of ſinging, the other of flouriſhing and painting. 7. As the Deaf man has this advantage above the Blind, that ſpeaking in common commerce, and buſineſs is of more frequent and greater uſe than writing: So the Blind man comes even again with him in this. That there is one way of writing, and that of great uſe too, to the Deaf man; which the blind can learn both aſſoon and to as great a degree of perfection, as the deaf; whereas the deaf man cannot learn to ſpeak without much time, and pains; and yet can never come to perfection in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. This way of writing is, by an Alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet upon the fingers. 8. As to any direct tendency of improving either of them with knowledg, or diſpatch of buſineſs and converſe <hi>in vita communi,</hi> I judge them both equally uſeleſs, or at leaſt of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:57291:20"/>no very great uſe; becauſe I think ſcarce attainable to that degree of perfection, as to be ready for uſe upon all occaſions. That there may be caſes wherein they may be of great uſe I do not deny.</p>
            <p>And of ſeveral that offer themſelves, I will ſingle out that of a blind Maſter, and deaf Servant, for ſtating of which the more clearly; I will premiſe. 1. That to read and write is a commendation in a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant. 2. It recommends him the more if he be to ſerve a blind Maſter. And 3. if his blind Maſter be a man of much buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or learning, this enhanſes his ſervice yet the more. Theſe things premiſed; let our caſe be this.</p>
            <p>Blind <hi>Homer</hi> hearing of an ingenious, but Deaf ſlave, called <hi>Aeſop,</hi> who was train<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up in all the forementioned waies of Sematology, and he himſelf being expert in Dactylology, he reſolved to purchaſe <hi>Aeſop</hi> at any rate. The firſt ſervice he puts him upon, was to write out his <hi>Ilias</hi> fair, from his own blotted Copy: And becauſe <hi>Aeſop</hi> could ſcarce read his hand, he was alwaies preſent himſelf, correcting the faults of his Pen, upon his fingers. And
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:57291:21"/>here I leave them for a while till I have reſolved another material doubt:</p>
            <p>That which is my main deſign in this Treatiſe (to teach how to come to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand a language by reading and writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) ſuggeſts to me here to reſolve this queſtion. How a blind perſon might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with a dumb? The cauſe of doubting being upon the dumb mans part. I anſwer. The defect of his Tongue muſt be ſupplied with a muſical Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, having the letters equally diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed upon the Keys, or Strings, both to the Eye of the Dumb, and in the ſounds to the Ear of the Blind; which I take for granted might produce the ſame effects with Oral ſpeech. And here it is obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able that that ſame action would very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be, both Writing and Speaking; writing from the hand of the dumb touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Keys, or Strings; ſpeaking to the Ears of the Blind man from the ſound of the Inſtrument.</p>
            <p>After this ſhort enterlude, let us bring <hi>Homer</hi> and <hi>Aeſop</hi> upon the ſtage again. The old man was mightily pleaſed with <hi>Aeſop,</hi> till unfortunately on a certain
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:57291:21"/>time, the ſtuttering of his Tongue gave <hi>Homer</hi> occaſion to ſuſpect him of a ly: for which, in a ſudden paſſion, he cuts out his Tongue: But afterwards repenting what he had done, reſolved not to put him away; for he conſidered that he was yet as capable of ſerving him as ever; and perhaps more, the other waies of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation that he was skilled in, being more diſtinct than Gloſſology could be in a Deaf man. It happened ſoon after that <hi>Homer</hi> had invited ſome friends to din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, commanding <hi>Aeſop</hi> to provide the greateſt rarities the Market did afford. <hi>Aeſop</hi> made a ſhow of great preparation; but ſet nothing upon the Table, beſide the tip of his own Tongue, in a large diſh; upbraiding his Maſter with his pipe, that he did not tear his blotted papers when he could not read them; but had pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence till he himſelf corrected them upon his fingers. <hi>Homer</hi> not enduring this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front before ſtrangers throws <hi>Aeſops</hi> pype in the fire. <hi>Aeſop</hi> fearing worſe to follow, throws himſelf at his Maſters feet taking him by the hand, and by the rules of Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tology begs his pardon, promiſing if he
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:57291:22"/>would have patience, to make amends for his fault. <hi>Homer</hi> ſtartled at this, to find both a Tongue, and a Pype, in <hi>Aeſops</hi> fingers; was tranſported from wrath to fear, and admiration, concluding for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, That <hi>Aeſop</hi> was a conjurer, and that he deſerved to be thrown in the fire after his pype. Yet reſolving once more to try his wit and honeſty: and for making ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to his friends who had loſt their dinner, he invites them to return to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, charging <hi>Aeſop</hi> to provide the oldeſt, and leaneſt carrion, he could find. The night following, <hi>Aeſop</hi> ſerves his blind Maſter with <hi>lex talionis</hi> tongue for tongue, and repeated the ſame dinner to his friends the next day; excuſing the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that he had from firſt to laſt obeyed his Maſters commands, to the beſt of his judgment. <hi>Homer</hi> taking it ill, to be ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ften outwitted by a ſlave, by Dactylology begs of his provoked friends, to revenge him upon <hi>Aeſop,</hi> by plucking out his Eyes; that his condition might not be more comfortable than his own. After this old age and a fit of ſickneſs deprived <hi>Homer</hi> of his Hearing. This reconciled him again to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:57291:22"/>
               <hi>Aeſop;</hi> for he judged him the fitteſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion he could find, with whom to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moan his folly, and miſery. After this, they lived good friends, paſſing the time in telling old ſtories; ſome times upon their fingers ends, and ſometimes with hand in hand, traverſing the Alphabeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal <hi>Ilias.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Drama</hi> being acted according to the Rules of Art, if there be any certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in Art, that the promiſed effects will follow, is no leſs true than it ſeems to be ſtrange. And from this we may learn two things. 1. That tho hearing and ſeeing be the Principal, yet are they not the only Senſes of Knowledg. 2. That the Hand is, (or at leaſt is capable of being made) a more ſerviceable organ of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation to the Soul than the tongue. For it has acceſs to its Miſtreſs's preſence, by the door of 3 Senſes. 1. Of hearing by Aulology. 2. Of ſeeing, by both Species of Schematology, to wit, Typology and Dactylology. 3. Of Feeling, by Haptolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy. Whereas the Tongue can only enter by the door of one Senſe, and do its meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage only by one kind of interpretation, Gloſſology.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:57291:23"/>
            <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Of a Deaf mans Capacity to underſtand the ſpeech of others.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I Come now to the Deaf mans capacity of underſtanding the ſpeech of others. That words might be gathered, and read from the tranſient motions, and configu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, of the mouth (if all the ſeveral diſtinctions of letters, were no leſs mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and apparent to the Eye, than to the Ear form the ſpeakers face) as readily as from permanent Characters upon paper, is not to be doubted: But that all the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions that are perceived by the Ear in ſpeaking, cannot equally be perceived by the Eye; I will prove by an argument, which tho it be <hi>à Poſteriori;</hi> yet I hope it will be of evidence and force ſufficient, to effect what is thereby intended.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If the ſame diſtinctions of letters and words did appear to the Eye from the motion of the ſpeakers mouth, which are diſcernable to the Ear from the articulation of his voice;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:57291:23"/>Then it would follow; That the capacity of a Deaf man, would be equal to that of a Dumb (but not Deaf) for learning a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, ſo far at leaſt as to underſtand it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the capacity of a Deaf man is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual to that of a Dumb, for learning a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage from ſpeaking.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore all the diſtinctions of letters, are not manifeſt to the Deaf, man from the ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſequel of the Major is, I think, clear from what has been ſaid before; there being nothing in ſounds to the Ear either Natural, or Symbolical, more than in motion and figures to the Eye. And if any ſhould ſay; That it is not ſo eaſy to read tranſient motions of the lips, even ſuppoſing them ſufficiently diſtinct (which muſt alwaies be ſuppoſed) as permanent Characters. To this firſt, I oppoſe reading from poynting to a finger Alphabet; which is nothing but motion. 2. All reading from whatſoever immovable object, is as proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly motion as hearing; for if there be no motion in the object, then it muſt be in the Organ of the Eye: which alters not our caſe, more than the Earths motion, or reſt,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:57291:24"/>alters the Phaenomena of Aſtronomy.</p>
            <p>If here it ſhould be urged; that granting Signs to the Eye to be as fit for teaching, as ſigns to the Ear; and therefore, that a Deaf perſon muſt be ſuppoſed to be in as great a capacity of learning to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand a language ſpoken, as a blind, when the diſtinctions to the Eye and Ear are the ſame; yet, that the blind man learns to underſtand a language from hearing others ſpeak, when the Deaf man learns not to underſtand from ſeeing others ſpeak; is from the advantages the Ear hath above the Eye.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, that all the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages the Ear hath over the Eye, will be conſiſtent enough with the Deaf mans ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of learning to underſtand a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage from ſpeaking. It is true here, that the Eye is ſtill at the loſs of equal oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of time with the ear; but the other advantage I gave the ear over the eye, of doing more work in leſs time, is here quite taken away: and yet the Deaf man will ſtill have as much opportunity of time (if there were no other defect) if his Nurſe and all that are about him be
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:57291:24"/>not <hi>Dumb,</hi> as ſufficiently to inculcate the common Notions of Language: For tho young people learn a Language by hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing others ſpeak; yet the greateſt part of what they hear is redundant, and like rain falling into a full conduit, runs over. So that a deaf man tho he have not ſo much opportunity of learning as a blind; yet has he opportunities enough, and to ſpare, for learning the common notions of language.</p>
            <p>Now for the <hi>minor</hi> ſo far as concerns the Deaf man, it is known by ſad experience, that he learns no language from his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or Nurſe. And for the Dumb perſon, tho I can bring no inſtance; yet the caſe ſeems to me ſo clear, that I think no body doubts of it, and therefore I will not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large to prove it.</p>
            <p>But tho the Deaf man be not able to perceive all the diſtinctions of letters, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther indeed is it poſſible for him, the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious motions by which ſome of them are differenced not appearing outwardly; yet if he be ingenious, I judge that he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives a great many; and therefore I doubt not but Deaf perſons underſtand
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:57291:25"/>many things, even without teaching, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than what they have from their Nurſe. Tho here I muſt add: That they could underſtand but very little from the motion of the lips, which when moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct muſt be full of ambiguity, and aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocalneſs to them, without other circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances concurring. For when dumb peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple make it appear, that they underſtand many things that paſs in diſcourſe where they are preſent, Children and fools can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be perſwaded but they Hear: Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious and ignorant people think they have a familiar Spirit: others deſpiſing the folly of the one, and impiety of the other, do judge, that they are able by the Eye, as diſtinctly to receive words from the ſpeakers mouth, as others by the Ear. But the truth is, what they underſtand, is from a concurrence of circumſtances, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of which are often as material, as the motion of the ſpeakers lips; ſuch as, his eyes, countenance, time, place, perſons, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>To determine what, or how many di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions of letters, the eye is able to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcover in the ſpeakers face; There can be no man ſo fit to reſolve this doubt, as the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:57291:25"/>Deaf man. And if there be no miſtake in that well known paſſage of Sir <hi>Kenelm Digby;</hi> A <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Deaf Lord hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy reſolved it ſo, as to refute and deſtroy all that I have ſaid. What is there ſaid of him, will amount to this. <hi>That the Eye can perceive all the diſtinctions of letters, in the ſpeakers face, which the Ear can do in his voice.</hi> I let paſs that which increaſeth the wonder: That this <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Lord ſhould be able not only to know ſtrange letters, in ſtrange languages, inſtantly; but alſo to be able to imitate them, tho he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been taught.</p>
            <p>To neglect the Teſtimony of a perſon both of Honor, and Learning, who was an ear and eye-witneſs of all he relates, and had nothing to byaſs him from what he judged to be exact truth; and which is more, calling to witneſs to that relation a perſon much greater than himſelf, and beyond all exception for veracity; This would not only be diſingenuous, but alſo arrogant. Therefore I will ſay what ſeems moſt probable to me for reconciling that relation to the truth. I will then firſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, That Sir <hi>Kenelm Digby</hi> had not
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:57291:26"/>much conſidered this weakneſs of human Nature, nor of the way to remedy it; and therefore might be the more credulous (for I find nothing of ſuſpition or cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that he might not be impoſed upon) and ready (as we are all in ſtrange things) to magnify this rare and wonderful Art, which, 'tis like, he had never ſeen nor heard of before; and perhaps had even judged ſuch performances impoſſible. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, I will ſuppoſe that the Prieſt the Lords Tutor was ambitious to ſet off his Art, with all the advantages poſſible, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo great a Perſonage as the Heir of the Crown of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things being ſuppoſed, I take it for granted that the Prieſt has uſed artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Leger-de-main,</hi> in theſe paſſages that ſeem moſt ſtrange. What theſe have been (ſuppoſing the matter of fact to be true) tho I was not there an eye-witneſs; yet, without conjuring, I can tell as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, as if I had been a ſpectator, or, an Actor in that Scene. 1. His keeping up diſcourſe with others, has been done in ſet forms, to acting of which he has been trained up before hand. 2. For returning
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:57291:26"/>any words that came from the mouth of another; this he has been prompted to by his Tutor, or any other ſtanding by, with a finger Alphabet. <hi>3.</hi> As for his Echo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing back <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>Welſh</hi> words, two things may be ſaid. Firſt, that he might have been taught to ſound theſe guttural let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; which occur often in theſe languages, and were as eaſy to him as any other let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters whatſoever: Or ſecondly, Becauſe it is there ſaid that the Prieſt affirmed, that he performed ſome things which were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Rules of his Art; I know nothing can be ſaid, but that he might perhaps chance upon the true found of theſe let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or ſomething near them; which the relator thought good to repreſent with all his other performances (becauſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed wonderful to thoſe that never had ſeen, or heard of the like, or knew by what art they were performed) to the greateſt advantage. As for his returning words whiſpered at the diſtance of the breadth of a large room, there is no new wonder in this; for whiſpering and ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loud were all one to him: But I ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect that this as well as other things, has
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:57291:27"/>been a ſet leſſon, or, the Prieſt did <hi>micare digitis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am not ignorant that many of Sir <hi>Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelms</hi> relations, are looked upon, as fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulous and Hyperbolical. Well, be it ſo, and let this be as fabulous as any of them. It is not the <hi>eſſe,</hi> but the <hi>poſſe</hi> of the ſtory, that I concern my ſelf to maintain. That ſeveral paſſages related there, are impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and other circumſtances very hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbolical; in that ſenſe, in which he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands them, I think, I have ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved: And yet, that the whole rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion might be true, in that ſenſe I have put upon it, I hope I have made no leſs evident.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:57291:27"/>
            <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of the moſt effectual way to fill a Deaf mans capacity.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HItherto I have been taking meaſures of the Deaf mans capacity. I come now to conſider of the way to fill it. And here my deſign is not to give a Methodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Syſteme of Grammatical Rules; But only ſuch general directions whereby an induſtrious Tutor may bring his deaf Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pil to the vulgar uſe and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of a language; That ſo he may be the more capable of receiving inſtruction in the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> from the Rules of Grammar, when his judgment is ripe for that ſtudy. Or more plainly; I intend to bring the way of teaching a deaf man to Read and Write, as near as poſſible, to that of teaching young ones to ſpeak and underſtand their Mother-tongue.</p>
            <p>I will begin with a Secret, containing the whole Myſtery of the Art of inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting deaf perſons. That is, I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:57291:28"/>ſuch a powerful Engine, as may be able to fill his head as full of the Image<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the world of words of mans mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as it is of the things of this viſible world created by Almighty God: which Engine ſhall have one property more, that it ſhall not fail of ſucceſs, even ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing both Maſter and Scholar to be the next degree to Dunces.</p>
            <p>Here methinks, I ſee the Reader ſmil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at this <hi>Fortunam Priami;</hi> and hear him whiſpering to himſelf, <hi>Parturiunt Montes,</hi> &amp;c. But I hope before I have done with my Notion, to reconcile him ſo far to it, as to bring him to judge that there is ſomething conſiderable in it: And tho at firſt he meet not with all that this <hi>hia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> may ſeem to have promiſed; yet at laſt he may meet with ſomething more than he expected. This powerful and ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Engine, is not the Tongue of the Learned, but the Hand of the DILI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GENT. The Hand of a <hi>diligent</hi> Tutor will not fail to make a <hi>Rich</hi> Scholar, if <hi>Copia verborum</hi> may deſerve the name of <hi>Riches. Diligence</hi> will be that ſame virtue in our Deaf ſcholars Tutor, that <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſthenes</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:57291:28"/>makes <hi>Action</hi> to be in his Eloquent Orator. Let the deaf child then have for his Nurſes, not the 9 Muſes, but the 9 Magpyes: Let him be ſent to School, not to <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but to <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Diligence you will ſay is powerful in all Arts. True it is; yet as a Handmaid: But here I think, that without a <hi>Catachreſis,</hi> I may call it the principal point of Art. This with very few directions from Art, will do the work effectually; all the fine Tricks of Art, which the wit of man can contrive, will be ineffectual without this. The only point of art here is, how to make an application to your deaf Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, by the ſame diſtinction of letters and words to his Eye, which appear to the Ears of others from words ſpoken; That is to know his letters, and to write them readily; Diligence will do the reſt. For Example: Let the ſame words be ſeen, and written as often by the Deaf man, as they have been heard and ſpoken by the Blind; if their faculties of memory and underſtanding be equal, the meaſure of knowledge alſo will be equal. But here it will be neceſſary that I explain what I mean by Diligence.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:57291:29"/>
            <p>By Diligence I underſtand two things. 1. That which is properly ſo called, both in the Maſter and Scholar. This Sir <hi>Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelm Digby</hi> calls much patience, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy in the experiment upon the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Lord. 2. Many other adventitious helps. I ſummed up the advantages the Ear hath above the Eye into theſe two. 1. Having more opportunities of time; 2. Doing more work in leſs time. Here I will ſhew how Diligence, with a few directions from Art, may in a good meaſure remedy this inequality.</p>
            <p>It is a received Maxim amongſt thoſe who have employed their thoughts, in that ſucceſleſs enquiry, about a perpetual motion. <hi>Reconcile time and ſtrength, and this will produce a perpetual motion.</hi> The application is eaſy from what I have ſaid before, comparing the Deaf man with the Blind. Let them have equal time, and force of acting, and their proficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy will be equal. That care and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence both in the general, and the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars following, may remedy this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equality, in a great meaſure, I think no body will doubt. Neither ought this to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:57291:29"/>be any diſcouragement, that the recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciling time and ſtrength, as to a Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trical equality, is not poſſible: For it is not here, as in the perpetual motion. There, if you fail of a minute, or a Dram, all your labour is loſt: Here nothing is loſt, but juſt ſo much as you come ſhort of him you compare with. How much this is, we will ſee by the particulars following.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If the deaf Scholar could be brought to ſpeak readily, this would leſſen the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equality of <hi>Force,</hi> by one half: and if it were poſſible, that he could read the Speakers words from his face, this would make a Geometrical equality of force, in the Eye and Ear; ſo that the only inequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity would be then, in time; the eye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing confined to light, bodily poſture, and diſtance; and out of theſe circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the deaf and dumb man were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly cured. But becauſe I am diſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of this cure for which I have given my reaſons chap. 4. I will confine my ſelf to reading, and writing, moſt properly ſo called, as both the more certain and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect cure.</p>
            <p>Here the firſt piece of diligence muſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:57291:30"/>be, <hi>frequens excercitatio Styli,</hi> that is, as I underſtand it in this place, <hi>uſing the pen and fingers much.</hi> If this be ſo neceſſary for forming an Orator, (as <hi>Cicero</hi> teaches us in his <hi>de Oratore,</hi> inculcating it with <hi>ut ſaepe jam dixi</hi>) who has the uſe of the two principal Organs of Eloquence entire; how much more muſt it here be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, where the Pen muſt be both pen, and tongue. Great care therefore muſt be taken, to keep your Scholar cloſe to the practice of writing; for until he can not only write, but alſo have got a quick hand, you muſt not think to make any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable progreſs with him. It is true, that it were poſſible to teach a deaf man to read, without teaching him to write; as one may learn to underſtand a language ſpoken and not to ſpeak it: But this would be but a half cure, and leave your Scholar uncapable of Society.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the conveniency of writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cannot alwaies be in a readineſs, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other great help will be, to have <hi>Tabulae deletiles,</hi> of ſtone or black wood, hanging up for expedition, in ſeveral convenient places. A third help will be, to have ſome
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:57291:30"/>common forms written in thoſe Tables, there to continue, and to be filled up as accaſion requires, like Virgils. <hi>Sic vos non vobis,</hi> &amp;c, ſuch as, <hi>where is? I pray give me? who? when? what?</hi> &amp;c. Theſe may ſerve not only for expedition, but by them alſo, your Scholar may be taught to vary. Pocket Table books may ſometimes be more ready then theſe. 4ly when neither of theſe is in a readineſs, then practice by an Alphabet upon the fingers; which by frequent practice, as it is the readieſt, ſo it may become the quickeſt way of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and communication with dumb perſons. But I ſhall have occaſion to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large more on this, chap. 8. 5ly. another piece of uſeful care will be, to keep him from any other way of Signing, than by Letters. 6ly, Add to this; that his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliars about him be officious in nothing, but by the intercourſe of letters, that is, either by Grammatology, or Dactylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy.</p>
            <p>If now laſtly, I can make it appear that Diligence out-weighs wit in our prſent caſe; I hope my former Flaſh will not be thought to have ended in ſmoke. And
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:57291:31"/>this, methinks, is eaſily underſtood from obvious and daily inſtances: Do not we ſee that young ones, tho of very weak parts for underſtanding Grammar, yet come aſſoon, and ſome of them ſooner, to underſtand and ſpeak a language by uſe, without art, than thoſe of ſtronger parts. One Boy has gone to School 7 years, and yet underſtands not the common ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents of Grammar; another in the half of that time, is able to expound an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and reſolve all the Grammaticati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that occur to a Title: take the ſame two at play, or in things where there is no occaſion to ſhew their learning, you will often find, that the ſlow boy, for the nimbleneſs of his Tongue, and <hi>Copia ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borum,</hi> may ſeem to exceed the other, as far as he doth him in art.</p>
            <p>Hence it will ſeem to follow; That the principal point of Art in teaching a ſlow Scholar, is, to uſe no other art but that of Diligence: and if ſo, a ſecond infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence will be: That there is none ſo fit to teach a ſlow Scholar, as a ſlow Maſter; That is, one Dunce to teach another. This I know will ſeem ridiculous and abſurd to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:57291:31"/>many; yet I declare, that I am much of this mind in earneſt, in our preſent caſe, where Grammar is excluded. For an acute man will be impatient, and not able to ſtoop ſo much as the other. And to clear this further; I think it will be eaſily aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to, that a pratling Nurſe, is a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Tutrix to her foſter-child, than the moſt profoundly learned Doctor in the Univerſity.</p>
            <p>My laſt inſtance therefore ſhall be. Take Maſter and Scholar qualified as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, adding <hi>Diligence,</hi> as I have deſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, and let a liberal reward be propoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Maſter; if the work be not effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually done, let me be the Dunce for them both.</p>
            <p>If therefore this cure may ſo eaſily be performed; what a reproach is it to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, that ſo little compaſſion is ſhewn to this infirmity of human nature; theſe wretched impotents being not only neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected in the point of education, like brutes; but alſo, as if this were not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſs enough, the laws of men do moſt inhumanly deprive them of many privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges wherein the comfort of life con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:57291:32"/>As for former ages, I confeſs they are to be excuſed: For tho (as I have been proving) <hi>Diligence</hi> be the principal point of Art; yet was this a ſecret to them: But in this knowing age, in which proofs have been given both at home and abroad, that this weakneſs is cureable in a good meaſure; and if the reaſons contained in theſe papers have any weight, curable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to perfection; ſo far at leaſt as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the better part of the man. That is, theſe impotents may not only be inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the common Notions of Language, which is the bond of human Society; but alſo from this foundation may be raiſed the ſuperſtructure of all other arts, which are either for uſe or ornament to human Nature. I ſay then; for us to neglect ſo worthy and noble an experiment, and ſo great an object of charity and compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; were at once to degenerate from the charity of our Anceſtors, and to make their ignorance preferable to our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:57291:32"/>
            <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of a Deaf Mans Dictionary.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THO a Diligent inculcating of the common Forms of a Language, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing no other Rule or Method but that of the Nurſery, would undoubtedly bring the Deaf man to underſtand, and write it, ſo as the Vulgar underſtand and ſpeak it. Yet ſome directions from Art (ſpecially if your Scholar be ingenious) will both facilitate the work, and do it much better. That is, it will make him underſtand the nature of words better, and ſo prepare him for the ſtudy of Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar; as alſo the nature of things, for which he ſees words ſubſtituted, and ſo prepare him for the purſuit of other Arts. I will therefore give a few ſuch directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whereby the Teacher abſtaining from Rules and words of Art, may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to produce the proper effects of Art in his Scholar. But firſt I will reſolve two preliminary Queries. 1. What language
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:57291:33"/>is eaſieſt to be learned? 2. And what lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage will be the moſt uſeful?</p>
            <p>For the firſt, a language of a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical Inſtitution, or a real Character, would be by much the moſt eaſy; as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing free from all anomoly aequivocal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, redundancy and unneceſſary Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matications: and the whole inſtitution being ſuited to the nature of things; this verbal knowledge, would not only come more eaſily; but alſo bring with it, much real knowledge.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, The language of greateſt uſe to be learned, will be that of the place where he lives, and of the people with whom he is to converſe. And here with us, the Deaf man has ſeveral advantages above other Nations. Firſt, that our <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> is freer from anomoly, and aequivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calneſs (at leaſt in writing, which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for him) than many other lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages. 2. It is not ſo much clogged with inflexions, as other languages, and 3. our words are for the moſt part Monoſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and therefore more eaſy to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred. I come now to the promiſed directions.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:57291:33"/>
            <p>I will make way for particulars, by ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving firſt in General; that the way of teaching here, muſt be ſomething mixt, and as it were middle between the Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical way of the School, and the more rude diſcipline of the Nurſery. The firſt initiation muſt be purely grammatical; But when your Scholar is got over this difficulty of knowing and writing his let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters readily; Then imitate the way of the Nurſery. Let <hi>utile</hi> and <hi>jucundum,</hi> varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and neceſſity, invite and ſpur him on; ſpecially if he be young or of a lache tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
            <p>You muſt not be too Grammatical in teaching, till you find his capacity will bear it: He muſt not be dealt with as School-boyes, who are often puniſhed for not learning what is above their capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. It is enough for him to underſtand the word, or ſentence propoſed, without parſing every word and ſyllable: For this is all the uſe of language that not only children, but even people of age that are illiterate have: They underſtand the meaning of what is ſpoken; but can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tell how many words, ſyllables, or
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:57291:34"/>letters came from the ſpeakers mouth. So that the having the vulgar uſe of a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage and the underſtanding it Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matically, are very different things. And this prepoſterous way of learning the learned languages, firſt Grammar, &amp; then the language, is the cauſe of ſo ſlow pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs in thoſe that apply themſelves to the ſtudy of them.</p>
            <p>The firſt exerciſe you muſt put your Scholar upon, is to know his letters writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, or printed, and upon his fingers, and to write them himſelf; and when he comes to joyn, let his copies be of ſuch words as he may be taught to underſtand; ſo that at once, he may be learning both to write and underſtand the meaning of what he writes. When you have got him to write fair, keep him to conſtant pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, that you may bring him to write a quick hand; which his condition re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires.</p>
            <p>Let him begin to learn the Names of Things beſt known to him, how Hetero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geneous ſoever; ſuch as the Elements, Minerals, Plants, Animals, Parts, Utenſils, Garments, Meats, &amp;c. and generally the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:57291:34"/>names of all ſuch corporeal Subſtances, Natural or Artificial; not only abſolute, but Relative, as <hi>Father, Brother, Maſter, Servant;</hi> as alſo names of offices, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, as <hi>Cook, Butler, Page, Groom, Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, Barber,</hi> &amp;c. For all theſe will be as eaſily apprehended as the moſt diſtinct <hi>Species</hi> of natural Bodies. Let his <hi>Nomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clature</hi> be written down fair, and careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſerved; not only in a book, but on one ſide of a ſheet of Paper, that it may be affixt over againſt his eye in conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent places. And let this his Dictionary be ſorted three waies. 1. Alphabetically, 2. following the order of double Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, both in the beginning and the end of a word. 3. Reducing it to ſeveral heads, or <hi>Claſſes,</hi> with reſpect not to the words, but the things, as in <hi>Junius Nomenclator,</hi> for every one of theſe Methods will be of good uſe to him.</p>
            <p>After he has got a good ſtock of theſe concrete Subſtantives, then proceed to Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectives; namly, Senſible Qualities, Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, with ſome Metaphyſical Notions; which all of them almoſt admit of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per contraries; which illuſtrate one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:57291:35"/>and therefore will be of great uſe to the learner. Let him be made to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand Adjectives by joyning them to their proper ſubjects, taken out of his vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabulary of Subſtantives already under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; as <hi>Hard Iron, Stone, Bone,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Soft Silk, Wool, Cloth,</hi> &amp;c. And ſometimes inſtance the two contraries, in that ſame Subject; as <hi>Iron hot, cold:</hi> And thus he will make a further advance to complex Notions.</p>
            <p>Obſerve here. That by the help of an Almanack and Watch, it will be eaſy to make your Scholar underſtand all the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences and words of that difficult Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After he has practiſed ſufficiently upon complex notions of Subſtantives, and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectives; let him proceed to words of Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whether bodily or Spiritual, which Grammarians call Verbs, as, <hi>break, cut, hold, take, laugh, affirm, deny, deſire, love, hate,</hi> &amp;c. And thus much ſhall be enough to have been ſaid of his Dictionary, in this rude diſcipline under which we ſuppoſe him as yet to be.</p>
            <p>Here I would have it well obſerved: That tho in applying my ſelf to the deaf
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:57291:35"/>mans Tutor, I have followed ſomething of Method, <hi>docendi Cauſa;</hi> yet I do not adviſe him, to take this courſe with his Scholar: But as I ſaid before, That the names of things beſt known to him, how heterogeneous ſoever, were to be firſt learned: So here I ſay, that there is no regard to be had to the cognation, or Grammatical affinity of words. In a word, occaſion will be the beſt Miſtreſs of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, till he have made a conſiderable ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance; And then when his Dictionary begins to be numerous, it will be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to draw it up in rank and file. Nay fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I am ſo far from adviſing to follow any method at firſt, but what is occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal (excepting only the ſtated, and fixt order of letters in the Alphabet) that if your Scholar be not very young, you may propoſe ſentences as early to him as ſingle words; eſpecially interrogatives and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratives, as, <hi>where is your hat? whoſe hat is this? who gave you this apple? Riſe up, ſit down, give me the cup, ſhut the door,</hi> &amp;c. And theſe may be eaſily varyed Indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, infinitively, affirmatively, nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:57291:36"/>
            <p>And yet for all this, I cannot deny but the Teacher may, and muſt contrive ſome method for himſelf, even of thoſe things which he has taught, following occaſion and his Pupils capacity; that he may know the better to take the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of his progreſs, and to make the beſt uſe of occaſions offered.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:57291:36"/>
            <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Of a Grammar for Deaf Perſons.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HAving diſpatcht the Deaf mans Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionary, I come in the next place to ſpeak of his Grammar. I ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict the principles I have formerly laid down, if I ſhould inſiſt much upon Grammar; neither indeed doth our <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Tongue require or afford much to be ſaid by him, who would be ambitious to ſhew himſelf <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore only make ſome few reflexions upon Etymology and Syntax, ſuppoſing Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thography to belong to Lexicography, of which already: And for Proſody, our Scholar is no more able to receive its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, than a blind man is to judge of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only take notice of <hi>5</hi> Etymolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical Grammatications, and do but name them; for I judge that theſe and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther points of Grammar are to be dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, at leaſt as to an accurate explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:57291:37"/>of them, until he be fitted for the ſtudy of Grammar, in manner as I have ſaid before.</p>
            <p>The firſt is the plural number for which the Rule is but one and eaſy. <hi>Add s to the ſingular, pen, pens,</hi> and the exceptions are not many, which here I paſs by. 2. The Comparative, and Superlative degree, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as eaſy as the other. They are form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by adding the terminations <hi>er</hi> and <hi>eſt,</hi> or by the auxiliary words, <hi>more, moſt,</hi> as hard <hi>harder hardeſt,</hi> or <hi>more</hi> hard <hi>moſt</hi> hard. The exceptions are not many. <hi>3.</hi> The Participle Active or Neuter in <hi>ing,</hi> from which I think there is no exception: And the Participle paſſive, which is often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the ſame with the preterimperfect Tenſe, without an Auxiliary word, as, I <hi>loved;</hi> or the preterperfect Tenſe, with an auxiliary word; as I have <hi>loved:</hi> But from this rule are a multitude of excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; which is the greateſt irregularity in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue. 4. The adverb of the manner ends in <hi>ly.</hi> This alſo hath its exceptions, but not many. <hi>5.</hi> The ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract ending in <hi>neſs,</hi> generally.</p>
            <p>Theſe things you need not teach your
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:57291:37"/>Scholar by Rule, for a little practice will enable him to make a Rule for himſelf, and to bring the exceptions too under his Rule; as, we hear Outlandiſh men, and children ſaying often: <hi>mans, womans foots,</hi> for <hi>men, women, feet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for that ambiguity, that almoſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very concrete Subſtantive in Engliſh is uſed verbaly, as <hi>pen, hand, foot,</hi> &amp;c. This adds much to the Copiouſneſs, Emphaſis and Elegancy of the language; and yet gives very little cauſe of miſtake; the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the words determining the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnification. But the Verbal ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe words being Metonymical, it will be beſt to leave them to their own place. So much for Etymology ſhall ſerve in this place, now for Syntax.</p>
            <p>The Learned languages make two ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral parts of Syntax, agreement and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mernment; whereas it ſeems to me that with them, Syntax requires a diſtribution antecedent to this. To wit, that the Syntax of words is either <hi>per ſe</hi> or <hi>per ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ud,</hi> i. e. The Grammatical coherence and connexion of words, is made by the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of the words themſelves, or,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:57291:38"/>by auxiliary words, called <hi>Particles.</hi> But neither the one nor the other of theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributions does our language require, or admit of, being freed from all incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances of inflexions, by genders, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes (except a few pronouns) and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently from the Rules of Agreement, and Government: All our Syntax con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in the cement of auxiliary Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</p>
            <p>To treat of Syntax then in Engliſh, is to ſhew the uſe of the <hi>Particles,</hi> in form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words into Sentences. For, to explain theſe Notions ſeparately, were to build Caſtles in the Air; and to form ſentences without them, were to make ropes of ſand.</p>
            <p>Here I will not inſiſt upon explaining every ſingle particle, as if I were dealing with a Dumb Scholar; But remembring that the preſent addreſs is more to the Maſter then the Scholar; I will inſtance only in ſome few, which may ſerve for a Clew to guide any ingenious adventurer thro the whole Labarynth.</p>
            <p>As I would adviſe the dumb Scholar to be often put to practice upon verbs of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily action, varying the circumſtances
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:57291:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>by the Particles; ſo will I ſingle out the verb <hi>Cut,</hi> to be the Principal verb in the following Examples, for explaining the Particles.</p>
            <p>I begin with Pronouns, which accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Notation of the word, are words put for other words. Let therefore theſe things be preſent, for whoſe names the pronouns are the <hi>provocabula:</hi> and then it will be eaſy to make your Scholar un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the uſe of theſe pronominal words. I will inſtance, firſt in the Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratives, <hi>I, thou, he, we, ye, they.</hi> Let there be ſix perſons preſent, as many more as you will. Write down. <hi>I cut, thou cut, he cut, we cut, ye cut, they cut.</hi> Let the Maſter take his Scholar by him, and place a third perſon over againſt him, all of them pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with a knife, and apple, or ſtick, &amp;c. Let the Maſter Cut firſt, pointing to the words <hi>I cut,</hi> 2. let the Scholar cut, the Maſter pointing to the words <hi>thou cut;</hi> 3. let the third perſon cut, pointing to <hi>he cut.</hi> And for the Plural number: let the Maſter and his Scholar ſtand firſt together, placing two more near them, and two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver againſt them. Then let the Maſter
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:57291:39"/>and Scholar cut, pointing to <hi>we cut;</hi> let the two by them cut, pointing to <hi>ye cut;</hi> 3. let the two over againſt them cut, pointing to <hi>they cut.</hi> The poſſeſſives, <hi>mine, thine, his, ours, yours, theirs,</hi> may be taught after the ſame manner; <hi>my apple, thy apple, his apple, our apple, your apple, their apple, mutatis mutandis.</hi> In ſhort, all pronominal words after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>all cut, none,</hi> or <hi>no body cut, this boy cut, that boy cut, the ſame boy cut, another boy cut, &amp;c.</hi> Let him practice much upon this and other Verbs till you find that he is able to make theſe diſtinctions of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>When he can diſtinguiſh perſons, it will be eaſy from many examples, <hi>cutteſt, cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, breakeſt, breaketh, holdeſt, holdeth,</hi> to make him underſtand, that the 2d and 3d perſon ſingular are diſtinguiſhed by termination from the other perſons.</p>
            <p>For the Signs of Tenſes, <hi>do, doſt, doth, have haſt hath, was waſt were, ſhall will:</hi> write down, <hi>I have cut the pen, I do cut the apple, I will cut the ſtick:</hi> cut accordingly pointing to your Scholar; or, write, <hi>I have ſtood, I do ſtand, I will ſtand,</hi> do accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:57291:39"/>
               <hi>I have walked, I do ſtand, I will ſit,</hi> do accordingly. Do not trouble your Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar with too nice diſtinctions of words, ſuch as <hi>ſhall</hi> and <hi>will, did</hi> and <hi>have;</hi> it is enough for him, as yet, that he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the uſe of words in the common forms of ſpeech, as illiterate perſons do.</p>
            <p>Let him practice much upon the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouns, and Signs of Tenſes, with Verbs of Action, adding other circumſtances of time, place, manner, &amp;c. and that with all the variety poſſible, of familiar, plain, eaſy, moſt common, and moſt frequently occurring circumſtances.</p>
            <p>The <hi>copula</hi> will be eaſily underſtood, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of its frequent uſe, both affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively and negatively; <hi>fire is hot, water is not hot; water is cold, fire is not cold;</hi> So in all its inflexions; as, <hi>I am tall, thou art ſhort, he is thick, I am ſitting, thou art ſtanding, he is walking.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Particles OR and, AND, with the adjectives <hi>Same</hi> and <hi>diverſe,</hi> are to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently inculcated, as being words of fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent uſe, and uſeful for explication, and declaring the ſenſe of other words. <hi>Or</hi> in the explicative ſenſe of it coming be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:57291:40"/>words ſignifying the ſame thing; <hi>And</hi> between words ſignifying diverſe things. It may be good to write down ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny examples of Synonymous words, and phraſes which your Scholar underſtands, joyning them with, <hi>or,</hi> as</p>
            <list>
               <item>The ſame
<list>
                     <item>I ſtand or</item>
                     <item>I do ſtand or</item>
                     <item>I am ſtanding</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>the ſame
<list>
                     <item>to go or</item>
                     <item>to walk</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>the ſame
<list>
                     <item>wide or</item>
                     <item>broad</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>So for the Copulative, AND, give ſuch examples as theſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Diverſe
<list>
                     <item>Hand <hi>and</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Foot</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>diverſe
<list>
                     <item>Pen <hi>and</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Ink</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>diverſe
<list>
                     <item>Sun <hi>and</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Moon.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>But the frequent recurring of theſe and many ſuch like in common, familiar, and neceſſary forms of ſpeech, will ſoon make them to be underſtood.</p>
            <p>As for Particles ſignifying Motion, as <hi>to, from, thro, by, into, out of, hither, thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hence, thence,</hi> &amp;c. whether prepoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or adverbs: ſo Diſtance, as, <hi>far off, near, at, hard by, cloſe by,</hi> &amp;c. Poſition, as, <hi>before, behind, above, upon, beneath, about, up, down, beyond, on this ſide,</hi> &amp;c. Their uſe and meaning is ſo plain and obvious, that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:57291:40"/>there needs no more but choice of fit ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to make them underſtood. The Table is <hi>before</hi> your face; The Chair is <hi>behind</hi> your back; The book is <hi>upon</hi> the Table; My hand is <hi>above</hi> the Table; the noſe is <hi>between</hi> the Eyes; the Eyes are <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove</hi> the mouth; the mouth is <hi>under</hi> the eyes; the tongue is <hi>in</hi> the mouth; to put <hi>out</hi> the tongue; to riſe <hi>up;</hi> to ſit <hi>down;</hi> go <hi>to</hi> the door, <hi>from</hi> the door, come <hi>hither,</hi> go <hi>thither,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe and ſuch like words ſignifying circumſtances perceivable by ſenſe, are as eaſily apprehended, as words ſignifying bodily ſubſtance or ſenſible Quality.</p>
            <p>Even the Particles of a Metaphyſical extraction, and more remote from ſenſe, may be eaſily underſtood, if the Teacher be not too Metaphyſical in his applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I will mention here only two To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picks of this kind of Particles; The cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and the Comparates, which are the two principal ſinews of diſcourſe. The particles from the cauſes are diverſe, <hi>from, of, with, by, wherefore, therefore, becauſe, why,</hi> &amp;c. Uſe examples ſuch as theſe. This Pen was made <hi>by</hi> the Maſter, <hi>of</hi> a Gooſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quil,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:57291:41"/>
               <hi>for</hi> to write <hi>after</hi> my Copy. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain <hi>why, wherefore, what is the cauſe,</hi> by expoſtulations, and interrogations, with your Scholar himſelf or others, and <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe</hi> in anſwer to theſe.</p>
            <p>Obſerve here, that many of theſe Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles being very equivocal, it will not be prudence to repreſent this difficulty all at once, leſt it a maze and diſcourage your Scholar. For example, you have made him underſtand the cauſal particle <hi>with,</hi> in ſuch examples as theſe, to cut <hi>with</hi> a knife; to write <hi>with</hi> a Pen: do not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly put him upon the Particle of Society <hi>with,</hi> as, go <hi>with</hi> me; but explain the various uſe of ſuch particles, as they offer themſelves occaſionally in practice, and as you find his capacity is able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive: For, improving of occaſions, and complying with the Scholars capacity, will be the Maſters greateſt commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Not but that he may be put upon learning many ſet forms for exerciſe of memory; tho he underſtand them not perfectly. But do not put his underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the rack, by an undiſcreet preſſing upon his apprehenſive faculty, Notions
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:57291:41"/>either ſimple or complex, which you find he receives not readily. But make a col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of ſuch words, and watch oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of explaining them: I can give no better Rule for explaining words hard to be underſtood; then that which <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>race</hi> has given, in a caſe not much unlike ours.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dixeris Egregie notum ſi callida verbum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Reddiderit junctura novum.</hi> —</l>
            </q>
            <p>Where the principal Verb of a ſentence is clearly apprehended, it brings great light to other circumſtantiating words. So that the skilful chuſing of verbs of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, well underſtood by your Scholar; and the like dexterity in placing a hard word, which you would have him to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, amongſt other words of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance already well underſtood, in conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with the verb; every word of the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence will reflect ſome light upon this dark word.</p>
            <p>The ſecond claſſis of Metaph: (or perhaps more properly Logical) parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, are thoſe that owe their Origine to the Topick of the Comparates; ſuch as, <hi>than, much, more, moſt, leſs, leaſt, by ſo
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:57291:42"/>much,</hi> &amp;c. explain theſe alſo by many fit examples, in which the ſeveral degrees of comparriſon may be demonſtrated to the ſenſes. This water is <hi>as</hi> hot <hi>as</hi> that; This cheeſe, apple, egg, is <hi>greater</hi> or <hi>more</hi> great <hi>than</hi> that; This apple is the <hi>greateſt,</hi> or <hi>moſt great</hi> of all the apples; <hi>by how much</hi> this ſtick, paper is <hi>longer than</hi> that, <hi>by ſo much</hi> that is <hi>broader than</hi> this; let the proportion be fitted and meaſured.</p>
            <p>It will be neceſſary to make a collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch forms of ſentences as he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands, one or two examples of every form, that upon occaſion he may have recourſe to them as to rules, and prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents in the like caſes: and amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forms, forget not imperatives and interrogatives, for which he will have ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and frequent uſe. Gather up all the forms of interrogation; <hi>when? who? what? where? whoſe? whence? whether? how long? many? great?</hi> &amp;c. Form ſentences upon every one of theſe interrogations, in things familiar; and ſubjoyn proper an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers; as, <hi>whoſe book is this?</hi> A. <hi>mine, thine, his, thy brothers, the Maſters,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>When ſhall we go to bed?</hi> A. <hi>by and by, at ten a
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:57291:42"/>clock, an hour hence,</hi> &amp;c. Imperative forms. <hi>I pray give me the book, take up the pen, lay down the paper, ſit down, riſe up, put on your hat, open the door, ſhut the door,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>For exerciſe, you may find great varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for him; ſuch as, to vary the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances propoſed; to deſcribe things from their cauſes, from their contraries, by comparing them with other things; To form a narration of things ſeen, to write Epiſtles. Let him be put much upon the exerciſe of memory; and that not only in looſe words, and incoherent ſentences; But let him beſtow much time and pains, in learning by heart, in the firſt place for his <hi>Lectiones ſacrae</hi> upon the Lords day, and Holy-dayes, the Lords Praier, the Creed, and ten Commandements, with the Church-Catechiſm.</p>
            <p>The ſolemnity and frequency of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service, would have good effects upon him, being placed conveniently op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the Miniſter, with a book before him, and one to direct him, till cuſtome enable him to direct himſelf. This would not only excite him to piety and devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but in progreſs of time, he would come
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:57291:43"/>both to underſtand, and have by heart, the greateſt part of Divine Service. Some other ſelect paſſages of Scripture might be recommended to him, as the firſt Chap. of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> the Hiſtory of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours Nativity, and ſufferings. The moſt proper books among profane Authors for him to practice on (I think) of many, were <hi>Aeſops</hi> Fables, and ſome playes where there is much of Action.</p>
            <p>In the application of all I have ſaid, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect is to be had to the quality of the perſon to be taught; whether young or old, dull or docile: How to comply with theſe circumſtances, muſt depend upon the prudence of the Teacher. When his progreſs is ſo conſiderable that it may be ſaid of him; He underſtands the Engliſh tongue tolerably well: He may then be put upon the ſtudy of Grammar; which will be the more eaſy to him; becauſe the courſe of ſtudy he was in before had a mixture of Grammar in it, as I have ſaid. Afterwards (or before if you pleaſe) he may be taught Arithmetick and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Geometry.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:57291:43"/>
            <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Of an Alphabet upon the Fingers.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>BEcauſe the conveniency of writing cannot alwaies be in readineſs; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet tho it could, is it ſo proper a <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium</hi> of interpretation between perſons preſent face to face, as a Hand-language: It will therefore be neceſſary to teach the Dumb Scholar a Finger-Alphabet; and this not only of ſingle letters, but alſo for the greater expedition, of double and triple Conſonants, with which our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh doth abound.</p>
            <p>After much ſearch and many changes, I have at laſt fixt upon a Finger, or Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alphabet according to my mind: For I think it cannot be conſiderably mended, either by my ſelf, or any other, (without making Tinkers work) for the purpoſes, for which I have intended it; that is, a diſtinct placing of, and eaſy pointing to the ſingle letters; with the like diſtinct, and eaſy abbreviation of double and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Conſonants.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:57291:44"/>
            <p>I deny not but there may be many more abbreviations than I have provided for, namely of initial Syllables, and Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations; but theſe I have paſt by at preſent, for two reaſons. Firſt, I think there will be little need of them; For I doubt not but that with the proviſion I have made, an habit equal to that in thoſe who write a quick hand, may very near make the Hand as ready an Interpreter, as the Tongue. 2ly. If they ſhould be judged needful, I have taken care, that with a few Rules they may be added, without altering any thing of the inſtitution of this preſent Scheme.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>diagram of a hand with the letters of the alphabet assigned to each part of it</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>I have made proviſion for abbreviating a threefold combination of them: I ſhall here only give the Rules of abbreviation of the ſeveral combinations I have made choice of, referring the reader for the reaſons of my choice, to the following Treatiſe of double Conſonants.</p>
            <p>The firſt combination of double Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonants I make proviſion for is, when <hi>h, l, r, s,</hi> come in one ſyllable with other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonants; and that two waies, either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore or after another Conſonant, as in theſe Examples.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. H.
<list>
                     <item>light</item>
                     <item>the</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2. L.
<list>
                     <item>ſalt</item>
                     <item>title</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>3. R.
<list>
                     <item>heart</item>
                     <item>trie</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>4. S.
<list>
                     <item>haſt</item>
                     <item>hats</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. When theſe 4 letters are prefixt to other Conſonants, as in <hi>light, ſalt, heart, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſt;</hi> the Rule is; <hi>point skin to skin with the four fingers of the other Hand reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Capital letter</hi> (which in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent example is T) <hi>to which they are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixt;</hi> which by Inſtitution deſigns the dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:57291:46"/>Conſonants <hi>ht, lt, rt, st.</hi> 2. When the ſame four letters follow another Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant as in, <hi>the, title, trie, hats;</hi> then, <hi>point</hi> (as before) <hi>to T with nail to skin,</hi> which gives, <hi>th, tl, tr, ts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond combination of double Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonants worthy of this care of abbrevia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe of their frequent uſe in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, is when the Liquids <hi>m, n,</hi> come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Mutes and Semimutes, <hi>b. p, d, t, g, k,</hi> or <hi>c,</hi> That is, <hi>m</hi> before <hi>b, p</hi> and <hi>n</hi> before <hi>d, t, g, k, c.</hi> The Rule is. <hi>Touch the place of theſe Mutes and Semimutes with the firſt and ſecond finger joyned;</hi> and this by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution gives the Liquid and the reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Mute or Semimute following, as in <hi>lamb, lamp, hand, hunt, anger, ink, France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third abbreviation is of Trible Conſonants in the beginning of a word or ſyllable, where <hi>s</hi> is alwaies the firſt; as in, <hi>ſchiſm, skrew, ſhrine, ſpread, ſtrong, ſcrag, ſphinx, ſoſthenes, ſplinter, juſtle,</hi> &amp;c. The Rule is, <hi>Joyn the thumb to the finger point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the other two Conſonants.</hi> And ſo much for abbreviation of double and trible Conſonants.</p>
            <p>But obſerve here, that as School-boyes
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:57291:46"/>are to learn <hi>a maviſſe,</hi> before <hi>a maſſe,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> before <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and to write words at length, before they learn ſhort-hand; ſo let your Dumb Scholar, and others that would practice Dactylology, firſt know, and practice upon the ſingle letters, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they come to practice upon the Rules of abbreviation.</p>
            <p>Now tho this way of ſhort-hand, or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breviation of words be diſtinct, eaſy, quick, and comprehenſive; yet is there another way of practiſing, which comes nothing ſhort of this in other reſpects, and in one reſpect ſeems to be preferable: That it ſuppoſes nothing neceſſary to be known for practiſing, but the places of the ſingle letters, without making new Rules for diſtinguiſhing double and trible Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, from the ſingle. The Rule is; <hi>Point to all the ſingle letters of the double or trible Conſonant, ſimul &amp; ſemel:</hi> which will be found to be as eaſy as poynting by the former inſtitution with one ſingle touch, as will appear in theſe examples; <hi>when, which, the, light, blunt, brand, grunt, plaſter, ſpread, ſtrong,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>If here it ſhould be objected, that this
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:57291:47"/>will breed confuſion, leaving the Reader doubtful what letter to begin with. To this I anſwer. 1. For double Conſonants in the beginning of a ſyllable, this obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction can never be of any force; for there is no Engliſh word found wherein their order is inverted, as will appear from the following Treatiſe of double Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants. 2. For double Conſonants in the end of a word, ſo far as concerns the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond combination formerly mentioned, there can never be any miſtake; for ſcarce (I think) is there any example occurs wherein their order is inverted; or if there did then the rule will be in that caſe, <hi>point to the ſingle letters diſtinctly.</hi> So that the objection is of no force, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept only againſt the firſt combination of double Conſonants, and that only in the end of a Syllable: For there are ſome, but not many examples, where the order is inverted as, <hi>ſalt title, haſt hats.</hi> But to this it may be anſwered: That in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſentence, the ſenſe will eaſily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the caſe, and take away all am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguity: as here lies one <hi>hat,</hi> there lie two <hi>hats.</hi> But if you have occaſion to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:57291:47"/>the word <hi>hats,</hi> from <hi>haſt,</hi> then you muſt point to all the letters diſtinctly.</p>
            <p>And this compendious and expeditious way of Cheirology may be extended fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, than this abbreviation of double and trible Conſonants: For they that are Maſters of a Language, and have got a conſiderable readineſs of practiſing, by diſtinct touches of ſingle letters, will find it as eaſy, as it is uſeful, to expreſs whole ſyllables, and whole words that are Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſyllables (ſpecially in words of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon uſe) with one multiplyed touch, <hi>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul</hi> and <hi>ſemel.</hi> My meaning by this mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed touch <hi>ſimul</hi> and <hi>ſemel</hi> is, not to touch diſtinctly all the letters of a ſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or word, by the <hi>Index</hi> or any one ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle finger of the other Hand ſucceſſively, making ſo many diſtinct motions from place to place, as there are letters in the ſyllable: But ſo to order the matter, that an equal number of the fingers of the other Hand may be uſed for a ſimultane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous touch to make the word or ſyllable, according to the number of letters it ſhall happen to conſiſt of. This way of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing ſyllables and words Monoſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:57291:48"/>with one multiplied touch, after a little practice, will be as eaſy and quick, as pointing to one ſingle letter with a ſingle touch; it will be alſo as diſtinct as pointing to every letter ſucceſſively, with one finger.</p>
            <p>But let it be well obſerved here, that tho I would have a whole ſyllable expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with one ſingle action, and motion of the whole Hand; yet let not the diſtinct touches be ſo ſimultaneous, but that it may appear where the word begins, and where it ends.</p>
            <p>Here I think will be a proper place to give a Rule, how to know when a word is ended, and it is this. <hi>Let there be a continued actual touch of more fingers, or one at leaſt, till the word be ended;</hi> or if this happen (as it may in ſome words) to be uneaſy, then make a quick motion from the place of the laſt letter of the word: But this difficulty after a little practice will vaniſh away.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe this diſcourſe may fall into the hands of ſome that have trifling Heads like my own, to whom it will be acceptable to know what other waies of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:57291:48"/>Dactylology I have had under conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: I will, for ſatisfying their curioſity, and perhaps ſaving them the expence of vain labour, mention ſome other waies which I have conſidered, and after exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation rejected.</p>
            <p>The firſt way is to make the figures of the letters upon the Hand, which differs only from writing in this; that the one is tranſient, and the other permanent. It is true, that this is more ready upnn all occaſions than writing; but neither di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct nor quick enough to be taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of here.</p>
            <p>A ſecond way is the forming of the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Symbolically; as to make an X by croſſing two fingers; a croſs touch upon the end of the thumb for a T; three fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers joyned for M, two fingers joyned for N, &amp;c. This Symbolical way I reject, as being defective in two reſpects: Firſt, it is defective in the point of ſymbolizing; for it will not be eaſy with the fingers to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the ſhapes of all letters. This way of expreſſing the letters Symbolically, is ſomewhat like the conceit of a ſymbolical Character, and a Language of Nature,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:57291:49"/>which ſome have talked much of; but without any foundation in Nature, and therefore all attempts of Art muſt be in vain. But ſecondly, this way is too labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and ſo defective in anſwering one of the principal ends for which Cheirolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy is deſirable, and deſerves the name of an Art: That is, a quick and ready ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and interpretation of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of the mind, coming as near as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to that of the Tongue.</p>
            <p>The third way is to deſign every ſingle letter by a ſingle touch; which I judge much the better way, than either of the other two; as being more ſimple, diſtinct, eaſy, and of quick diſpatch. Having therefore reſolved upon this, that the moſt proper way to expreſs the ſimple Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Alphabet would be, by a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle touch; it remained that they ſhould be diſtinguiſhed amongſt themſelves by their places. And here again, after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration and tryal, I have rejected ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral waies of diſtinguiſhing the letters by places. Firſt, I provided places on both Hands, back and fore; but finding this laborious and intricate, and perceiving
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:57291:49"/>that there might be diſtinction enough found in one hand, I placed the whole Alphabet upon one Hand; yet ſo as to make uſe of an equal number of places on both ſides of the Hand: But at laſt find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that all the neceſſary diſtinctions could be provided for, on one ſide of the Hand, I fixt upon the inſtitution of the preſent Scheme; which I think is done with that conſideration and care, that as I ſaid before, it cannot be much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved.</p>
            <p>Here I thought to have kept one ſecret of Art to my ſelf; at leaſt till I ſhould ſee how other things I had diſcovered ſhould pleaſe: But I muſt confeſs my own weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that in things of this Nature, I am <hi>plenus rimarum.</hi> I know not how conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable this ſecret will ſeem to others; But I declare (that I may confeſs another weakneſs) that I was much affected with it: For after a long and tyreſome chaſe, and having purſued my Notion, as I thought, to a <hi>nil ultra;</hi> when I was ſet down, and pleaſing my ſelf with my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe; on a ſudden I fancied my ſelf to ſee an one-handed deaf man coming to me,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:57291:50"/>and aſmuch as I could read in his eyes and countenance, expoſtulating with me thus? What? Have you done? Is there no help for me? Shall one Eye ſerve in Schematology? &amp; one Ear in Pneumatology? one tongue in Gloſſology? yea one hand in Typology? and ſhall not one Hand ſerve in Dactylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy? With this fixing my Eyes ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on his Hand ſtretched out, I thought with my ſelf, that I could diſcern a Mouth and a Tongue in his Hand: the Thumb ſeemed to repreſent the Tongue, the Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and the hollow of the Hand the lips, teeth, and cavity of the Mouth. Upon this I made Signs to him to try to follow me, as I pointed to the letters on my own Hand; which he did ſo exactly that the ſurpriſe put me in a maze for ſome time. But when I had overcome my paſſion, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting upon this wonder both of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Art, I obſerved that of the 24 letters, he pointed to 16 with his Thumb. Thus I diſmiſſed my Deaf and lame pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, bidding him be of good courage, and live in hopes of an effectual and ſpeedy cure.</p>
            <p>But after he was gone, I began to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:57291:50"/>with my ſelf. What? ſhall I magnify this as a myſtery and wonder of Nature and Art, to find a way, to Metamorphize a <hi>Chymaera</hi> into a Man, or, to make a black Swan white? This will be <hi>magno conatu magnas nugas agere.</hi> As I was thus thinking, it happened that I was ſmok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a pype of Tobacco; and having a preſent occaſion to diſpatch a ſpeedy meſſage; I was unwilling to let my Pype go out, and ſo at that preſent was depriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed both of the uſe of my Tongue and one Hand: wherefore reflecting upon the leſſon which I had lately taught the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handed Deaf man, or ſhall I rather ſay, which he taught me; I call a boy to me, whom I had trained up in Dactylology, and delivered my meſſage to him with one Hand. He ſtaring in my face with a ſmiling countenance (for I had never ſpoken to him before that time with one Hand) performed the meſſage very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, and returned me a ſpeedy anſwer, uſing the ſame Organ of Interpretation (for I ſurpriſed him eating an Apple) to me, which I had done to him. This gave me occaſion to think, that this point of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:57291:51"/>Art had not only one-handed Deaf men for its Object; but that there might be many other caſes wherein it might be uſeful to ſpeak with one hand: as to ſpeak to a Dumb man riding on Horſe-back, holding the reins with one hand, and with the other asking him. <hi>How do you do?</hi> or ſitting at Table; holding the Cup with one hand, and with the other ſaying, <hi>Sir my ſervice to you.</hi> Or, with one hand holding the knife, and with the other asking; <hi>what will you be pleaſed to have?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And if any man could be ſuppoſed to have that readineſs and preſence of mind which is ſaid to have been in <hi>J. Caeſar</hi> he might at once keep up diſcourſe with 3 ſeveral perſons, upon ſeveral ſubjects, talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to two with his two hands, and to a third with his Tongue. And here by the by, it is obſervable, that without any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction of mind one may ſpeak both to a Deaf and Blind man at once, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the <hi>ſame</hi> words by the Tongue to the Blind man, and by the hand to the Deaf.</p>
            <p>Nay further I declare, that as much as I have as yet been able to diſcover by pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, I judge the way of ſpeaking with
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:57291:51"/>one hand preferable to the other of uſing both, and that in all reſpects, unleſs it be in this one; That it is not capable of diſtinction enough for all the neceſſary abbrevations of double Conſonants, which perhaps (after a readineſs and habit ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired) may not be needful; or if it were, yet I know that one hand is capable of many more diſtinctions than I have as yet made uſe of: but at preſent I think it not <hi>tanti</hi> to make uſe of them, for I foreſee, that the conveniency will ſcarce ballance the inconveniencies.</p>
            <p>Now tho the practiſing of this Hand-language be ſo plain and eaſy from the following Scheme, and the preceding explication of it, that any one who can but read (without knowing to write) may become his own Teacher; yet ſeeing the nature of all skill and cunning deſerving the name of an <hi>Art</hi> is ſuch, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of inſtruction <hi>viva voce,</hi> is, if not neceſſary, at leaſt uſeful; So here ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of direction from one well skilled in the practice of this Art, either <hi>viva voce,</hi> or (which is the ſame thing, and as Emphatick a way of teaching if it were
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:57291:52"/>practiced) <hi>digito demonſtrante,</hi> will be of good uſe to young practitioners.</p>
            <p>I will add one help more, for enabling young beginners to practice more eaſily and readily: Let a pair of Gloves be made, one for the Maſter, and another for the Scholar, with the letters written upon them in ſuch order as appears in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Scheme. To practice with theſe, will be eaſy for any that do but know their letters and can ſpell; and a ſhort time will ſo fix the places of the letters in the Memory, that the Gloves may be thrown away as uſeleſs.</p>
            <p>Having laid open the whole progreſs of my thoughts in this diſcovery of Cheiro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, it remains that I make good my promiſe in the Title-page of ſhewing, that it is uſeful both in caſes of neceſſity and conveniency.</p>
            <p>Firſt then I think none will deny, but that it is neceſſary for perſons <hi>Deaf</hi> or <hi>Dumb;</hi> and therefore I ſhall ſpare my ſelf the labour of proving it any other way, than by referring the Reader to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and ſcope of this whole diſcourſe. But here it will be very proper to add ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:57291:52"/>how it may be made <hi>moſt</hi> uſeful to the Deaf man, and in order to this let it be conſidered. That the nature of Chei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rology is ſuch, that it is only uſeful in ſociety and converſe with others: So that if the Deaf man be trained up in this Art, and have no body about him skilled in it but himſelf, it is of no uſe to him at all: As on the contrary, if all people were as ready in this Hand-language, as he may rationally be ſuppoſed to be; then the Hand between him and others, would be of the ſame uſe that the Tongue is to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther people amongſt themſelves. But ſeeing (according to the received way of training up youth hitherto, by which no care is taken of teaching them Cheirolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy) he can have none, or very few to converſe with him in this way: It will be the concern of the Deaf perſons friends (beſide the influencing all his familiars to acquaint themſelves with this Art for his cauſe) to chuſe ſome fit perſon to be a conſtant companion to him, and to be his Interpreter upon all occaſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſtrangers. And which is yet a more weighty concern: It would be their
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:57291:53"/>wiſdom to project a match for the Deaf perſon, <hi>man</hi> or <hi>woman</hi> betimes; that the perſon they are to match with, may be trained up in Cheirology, which would add very much to the comfort of their life; they being thereby able to expreſs and communicate their ſentiments intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligibly, not only by Dactylology in the <hi>light,</hi> but alſo by Haptology in the <hi>dark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond place I am obliged to ſhew the general uſefulneſs and conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency of this Art to all mankind. The particular caſes wherein it may be conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, are many more than can be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, that I ſhould inſtance in: I ſhall therefore mention only three generals. 1. Silence. 2. Secrecy. 3. Pleaſure. In ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of neceſſary Silence, it may be uſeful to inferiors in the preſence of Great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; to thoſe that are about ſick peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as near relations, Nurſes, &amp;c. So for Secrecy, if people be in company, but not ſo near as to whiſper one another in the Ear, it performs the office of whiſpering; it delivers, and receives ſecret meſſages, &amp;c. And laſtly for pleaſure; it may be an ingenioius and uſeful divertiſement
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:57291:53"/>and paſs-time for young people.</p>
            <p>Here it may be objected, That all the conveniency will not ballance the pains that muſt be taken in learning this Art. This objection puts me in mind of another, and that a very conſiderable Convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; and therefore I anſwer. The pains that is taken about learning a Hand-lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, if it were learned in due time, that is, in Childhood, would be ſo far from hindring, that it would contribute much to the Childs progreſs in learning to read, if he were taught both to know his letters, and to ſpell upon his fingers. This would pleaſe the Childs fancy, and imprint the letters the ſooner upon his memory, having his Book alwaies open before his Eyes. So that I look upon this as the greateſt conveniency of Cheirology, That it would be of ſo great uſe, and learned with ſo little pains.</p>
            <p>And this conſideration put me upon thinking of a more adviſeable way of training up young ones, than any yet practiſed, that is: To begin children to know their letters upon an Hand-book inſtead of an Horn-book; or at leaſt to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:57291:54"/>have a Hand-book upon the backſide of their Horn-book: For I make no doubt but before they could come to know the names and Figures of the letters, they would know their places upon the Hand, and be able to point to them with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or the ſame Hand, as readily as to pronounce them with the Tongue.</p>
            <p>And who will not acknowledg that it were a thing deſirable, and deſervedly to be eſteemed as a peice of liberal educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; to be able to ſpeak as readily with the Hand as with the Tongue? And therefore who would not think it worth the while, to train up young children from their a bc in Gloſſology and Chei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rology, <hi>pari paſſu?</hi> ſpecially ſeeing the one is no hinderance but a conſiderable help to the other, for I may truly ſay in the Poets words,
<q>
                  <l>— <hi>Alterius nam</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Altera poſcit opem res, &amp; conjurat amice.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I thought for the uſe of children, to have given ſome directions for facilitat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Elementary Diſcipline of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the letters, ſpelling, and reading; whereby not only the old way might be
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:57291:54"/>made much ſmoother, but alſo by one and the ſame labour, a conſiderable acceſſion of uſeful knowledge might be attained by the young Scholar: That is, together with reading in Books, reading on the Hand; and as a neceſſary appendage of this, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon, or ſpeaking with (call it which you will) the Hand: whereas writing with the Hand according to the common uſe of the word is by it ſelf a diſtinct and laborious Art. But I fear leſt ſome may think that I have already ſtuft this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe too much with trifles, and pedan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb facs="tcp:57291:55"/>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:57291:55"/>
            <head>AN APPENDIX TO CHEIROLOGY. Containing Some Critical obſervations upon the Nature and number of Double and Trible Conſonants.</head>
            <p>MUCH hath been ſaid by many learned men to deſcribe the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and cauſes of Simple Sounds, which are the firſt Elements of Speech; as alſo of Diphthongs and Triphthongs (if any ſuch be) coaleſcing of 2 or 3 Vowels into one Syllable: But of the coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition of two or more Conſonants into one Syllable, little or nothing (for what I know) hath been ſaid by any. And yet this compoſition of Conſonants deſerves as much to be explained, or rather more
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:57291:56"/>than the other of vowels, becauſe of its greater variety and uſe; Eſpecially by him who would treat of a Philoſophical Language or a Grammar for Deaf per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: So that my firſt Treatiſe of <hi>Ars Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnorum</hi> or Sematology with this ſecond of Cheirology which is a legittimate off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of that, obliged me to this enquiry.</p>
            <p>If the Queſtion ſhould be put: whether in framing of words it were a more ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal inſtitution, that a ſingle Conſonant, and a ſingle Vowel ſhould alwaies ſucceed one another alternatly; or that there ſhould be a mixture of Syllables allowed, made partly of Diphthongs, partly of double conſonants? My own judgment in the caſe is. That both Nature and Art would make their firſt choice of an alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſucceſſion of ſingle Vowels and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonants, and that their next choice would be, of ſuch compounded vocal ſounds, as are commonly called Diphthongs, and deſcribed by Grammarians; and ſuch compounded cloſe ſounds, as are moſt natural, and of an eaſy pronounciation, for deſcribing of which this diſcourſe is intended.</p>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:57291:56"/>
            <p>But that ſuch a Language could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive its origine from blinded Nature, and not from Art, or a Divine inſtitution, is no waies probable: For I conceive that there is now no Language upon the face of the Earth in common uſe, but admits of a mixt compoſition of Diphthongs, and Double Conſonants. And the more rude and uncivilized the people are, the more frequent this compoſition is with them, and the ſounds the more harſh and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant. That roughneſs of ſpeech wears out with roughneſs of Manners, and ſmoothneſs of the one is a natural conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of the ſmoothneſs of the other, the Engliſh Language and Nation is a ſufficient proof. And if this be granted it is argument enough to prove; that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture without Art or ſome more powerful aſſiſtance, would never bring forth a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage in which there ſhould be no Diph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thongs or, Double Conſonants. Nature, I ſay, as it is now in its degenerate eſtate: How ſhe would have decided this Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in her primitive integrity and perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or rather how ſhe did actually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide it, as we are aſſured from Gods word
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:57291:57"/>ſhe did, cannot be otherwaies known to us, than by ſome probable conjectures.</p>
            <p>It is generally thought by the learned, that <hi>Adam</hi> was the Author both by Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Practice of the Hebrew Tongue; not as we have it now in any of its Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects; yet if it be granted that the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew had for its mother that Language which <hi>Adam</hi> did invent and ſpeak; we may with good reaſon conclude, that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted as it is, it ſtill retains the ſubſtance and <hi>Genius</hi> of its Mother; There being ſome indelible Characters upon all Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages which common accidents cannot deface. For tho the tract of time from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> was longer than that from <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> or <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, to this preſent age; yet the common ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents which are known to change a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage could not be ſo many and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, for changing the firſt language to that which is now called Hebrew, as they have been known to be for changing the pure Greek, into that which now is uſed by a remnant of the Grecians, and called Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Greek; or for changing the pure Latin <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tant</hi> in Claſſick Authors, into
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:57291:57"/>that which is now called Italian; which languages notwithſtanding keep ſtill ſo manifeſt Signatures of their origine, that it is eaſy to diſcern what Stem they are branches of.</p>
            <p>Now amongſt ſeveral other defaced re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of that firſt and Divine language remaining not only in the Hebrew, but alſo to be found in many other of the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Languages, this ſeems to be very conſiderable. That the Hebrew admits of no compoſition either of Vowels or Conſonants in that ſame Syllable; But all their Radical words conſiſt generally of a ſingle conſonant, and a ſingle vowel, ſucceeding one another alternatly; which cannot well be ſuppoſed to be the effect either of degenerate Reaſon or Chance.</p>
            <p>There are two things more in that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient language which ſeem to me unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable without referring them to a ſupernatural cauſe. One is, that their radical words conſiſt generally of 3 con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonants, and for the moſt part are Diſſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lables; and theſe Radical words how dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent ſoever in their conſonants, yet have ſtill the ſame points, <hi>Cametz</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thach;</hi>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:57291:58"/>which in oral prolation make the ſame vocal ſound with א, which, as it is the firſt letter of their Alphabet, and from them in all other Languages; ſo is it the firſt vocal ſound in Nature. And that originally all their words were Diſſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles (as ſome conjecture) is not impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable: whereas in all other Languages their Radicals are generally Monoſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and I think originally have all been ſo; yea ſo far ſo, that there are many Monoſyllables found to be <hi>Compoſita,</hi> and <hi>Decompoſita,</hi> as the Learned <hi>Doctor Wallis</hi> has ingeniouſly obſerved in his Engliſh Grammar.</p>
            <p>Another thing is, that the Hebrew does often contract a whole ſentence into one word, incorporating not only pronouns both prefixt and ſuffixt, but alſo prepoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and conjunctions with the radical word. And this <hi>compendium</hi> did firſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite me to do ſomething for improving the Art of Short-hand; That drove me before I was aware upon a real Character; That again after a little conſideration re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved it ſelf into an Effable language. This at laſt has carried on my thoughts to
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:57291:58"/>conſider of a way how a language may be attained by Reading and Writing, when it cannot be attained by Speaking and Hearing. So that this Series and chaine of thoughts has for its firſt link an Hebrew Grammatication.</p>
            <p>I take notice of three things more in the Hebrew, which are conſiderable upon the account of a rational Inſtitution, which is not to be found in the common uſage of other Languages; but not ſo myſterious as the other three which I have already mentioned. The firſt is their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parating the Vowels from the Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, both by place and Character; which has ſomething Natural, and Symbolical in it: For there is ſomething in the ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture and compoſition of the words, ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagous to <hi>Man</hi> the Author of them; the Characters of the conſonants being of large dimenſions, and diviſible into ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny parts, repreſent the groſs and material part of Man, the <hi>Body:</hi> The Vowels be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing expreſt by indiviſible pricks or points, do anſwer to that which is more properly indiviſible, the <hi>Soul.</hi> This, together with a more accurate diſtinction of Vowels into
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:57291:59"/>long and ſhort; as alſo a more accurate diviſion of Conſonants from their Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal cauſes, that is, the Organs of forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, tho of late uſe (according to ſome later writers) in that moſt ancient lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; yet it ſhows (at leaſt) how the <hi>Genius</hi> of the Tongue is fitted not only to comply with ſuch an Inſtitution; but alſo that from all Antiquity there have been ſome <hi>veſtigia</hi> of that Primitive and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, or purely rational Sematology, taught by Almighty God, or invented by <hi>Adam</hi> before the fall (unleſs any ſhould have the confidence to affirm, that this among many other unhappy conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the fall, was one; that it did not only in part deface, but totally wipe out all former impreſſions, leaving our firſt Parent as the blind Heathens would have him, <hi>Mutum &amp; turpe pecus.</hi> That is, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Soul as much <hi>Tabula raſa,</hi> as ours is when we come into the world) which have given occaſion to Grammarians of later times to bring that part of Grammar to the preſent eſtabliſhment. But what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever be the deciſion of that grand con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy about the Antiquity of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:57291:59"/>points, the obſervation I have made here will ſtill be conſiderable. Wherefore I paſs to a ſecond thing conſiderable, which without all controverſy is more ancient and of longer ſtanding than ſome would have the points to be. It is agreed upon all hands that there are three prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal and cardinal Vowels א י ו of as anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent a date as the firſt invention of letters; which without giving offence to thoſe that are for, or advantage to thoſe that are againſt the Antiquity of Points, may <hi>ſano ſenſu,</hi> be ſtyled <hi>Matres Lectionis;</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all other Vowels are but intermedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate ſounds and as it were the <hi>Proles</hi> or of spring of theſe three. Wherefore, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out interpoſing as to the main ſtate of that ſo momentous queſtion; That which I take notice of here as conſiderable, is this: That it has been a thing done with great care and judgment, the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe three letters for the Cardinal vowels or <hi>Matres Lectionis;</hi> For they are the three moſt diſtinct vocal Sounds that are in nature; even as diſtinct as the two extremes and the middle of any thing that has dimenſions can be; all other
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:57291:60"/>Vowels being but intermediate Sounds to, and gradually differing from them. א is a Guttural Sound, and of all other Vowels the moſt apert; ו is Labial and of Vocal Sounds the moſt contracted, י is Palatine and equally diſtant from both. And as it is poſſible that there might be a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage copious enough, allowing only the uſe of three Vowels, and ſecluding dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Conſonants in that ſame ſyllable, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided that the Radical words were Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyllables; which ſome think to have been the Inſtitution of the pure and uncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Hebrew: So would ſuch an inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuion be much more eaſy and diſtinct than any language in being; the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate ſounds to theſe three radical vowels being leſs diſtinct, and therefore oftentimes giving occaſion of miſtakes.</p>
            <p>I have had occaſion to mention the third thing conſiderable in the preceding Treatiſe of Cheirology; to wit, Their naming the ſimple Elements of letters by ſignificant words; <hi>Aleph, Beth, Gimel,</hi> &amp;c. which without doubt is as ancient as the uſe of letters, or at leaſt as <hi>Moſes;</hi> The truth of this the Grecians have confirmed
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:57291:60"/>by a very convincing, but withal a very inartificial argument in naming the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters corruptedly after them, <hi>Alpha, Beta, Gamma,</hi> &amp;c. as I have noted before.</p>
            <p>Tho I have in <hi>Ars Signorum</hi> given ſuch an Analyſis of ſimple Sounds, both Vowels and Conſonants, as ſeemed to me moſt natural and proper upon that occaſion; yet I muſt here repeat what has been ſaid there of the nature and number of ſimple Conſonants; otherwiſe the Rules of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition I am to give, cannot be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood.</p>
            <p>Conſonants then are firſt to be divided into,
<list>
                  <item>cloſe:</item>
                  <item>ſemicloſe.</item>
               </list> 1. Cloſe, when the appulſe of the Organs ſtops all paſſage of breath thro the mouth; and they are in number 9, <hi>m, b, p, n, d, t, ng,</hi> Γ, K, This clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure again is threefold. 1. A perfect ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the lips and this produces <hi>m, b, p,</hi> 2. the fore part of the Tongue with the Palate, hence <hi>n, d, t,</hi> 3. the hinder-part of the Tongue with the Palat hence, <hi>ng,</hi> Γ, K. Teſe nine Conſonants are capable of another threefold diviſion, upon the account of a threefold accident which
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:57291:61"/>equally happens to the foreſaid cloſure of the Organs reſpectively. For, 1. if the breath and voice be <hi>ſimul</hi> and <hi>ſemel</hi> ſtopt with the cloſure of the Organs, like the throwing of a ſtone againſt a Rock; this produces the 3 mutes <hi>aP, aT, aK,</hi> 2. If after the cloſure of the organs, a <hi>conatus</hi> of breathing be continued, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>percuſſion of the breath from the paſſage ſtopt, making an inward murmuring like the breaking of a wave againſt a Rock, which is quickly ſpent and huſht into ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; the ſame cloſure of organs produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the 3 Semimutes, <hi>aB, aD, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 3. If upon the cloſure of the organs, there be a free paſſage of breath and voice thro the Noſe, like the ſounding of an Organ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pipe, when the key is touched; this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces a third diſtinction of Sonorous let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from the ſame cloſure, <hi>aM, aN, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> G,</hi> (by <hi>ng</hi> I mean that ſound which is heard in <hi>anger, hunger</hi> not in <hi>danger, hinge.</hi>) And theſe 3 ſounds may be continued af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the cloſure of the Organs, as long as one will. I have placed a vowel before theſe conſonants, becauſe their <hi>power</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears more diſtinctly, than when the vowel follows.</p>
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:57291:61"/>
            <p>Hence I infer, that the number of cloſe conſonants is 9, neither more nor leſs; not more I ſay, becauſe I find that ſome add 3 more, <hi>hm, hn, hng,</hi> calling them Mutes, making only this difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them and, <hi>m, n, ng,</hi> that the one is uttered vocally, the other whiſperingly: But if a whiſpering and a vocal breath make diſtinct letters, there will be more diſtinctions of letters than the Authors of this opinion ſeem to approve: and if this be reaſon enough to multiply letters, I know not but ſoft ſpeaking, and crying about the Streets may have the ſame pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. That certain other diſtinctions in the forming of theſe, or any other letters, may be fancied by curious and Muſical ears, from the modes and degrees of ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the organs, the intention and remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the voice, the Tone being more grave, acute, &amp;c. I readily grant: But how to make more diſtinctions from theſe 3 cloſures, plain and eaſy to be diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and worthy to be ſo far taken notice of, as to be placed in the Alphabet, is a thing I could never reach.</p>
            <p>Again, I ſaid no leſs than 9, becauſe
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:57291:62"/>common cuſtome has made one of theſe a double Conſonant, writing it with two letters <hi>ng</hi> the ſound of neither of which is to be heard in pronounciation; but a perfectly diſtinct ſimple ſound from the power of both, as in <hi>ſing, ring, long,</hi> and from all letters whatever. And it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable that our Engliſh is very uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in expreſſing the power of this let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: ſometimes by <hi>ng</hi> in the end of a word, as <hi>ſing, hang, long;</hi> where nothing of the ſound either of <hi>n,</hi> or <hi>g</hi> is heard; Sometimes by <hi>n</hi> alone before its brother conſonants, <hi>k, g,</hi> before <hi>k</hi> every where; as <hi>ink, rank, drunk,</hi> before <hi>g</hi> in the middle of a word, as <hi>longer, hunger,</hi> tho not alwaies ſo, for in <hi>danger, ſtranger,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>n</hi> keeps its own power.</p>
            <p>If any be ſo far prejudiced with the uſe of the Latin (which alwaies expreſſes the power of this letter by <hi>n</hi>) and other mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Languages; let him look a little higher to the Greek, where he will find three things conſiderable of this letter. 1. That it is no double conſonant, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt with one ſingle Character, Υ. 2. That it is expreſt not by a letter of a diſtinct
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:57291:62"/>tribe (as in the Latin) but by one of its own fraternity, that is, by a letter form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the ſame cloſure of the organs with it ſelf. 3. That it never goes before any other conſonant in that ſame Sylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but thoſe of its own tribe Υ π Χ ξ; which is according to the true reaſon and Rules of compounding conſonants in the end of a ſyllable, as I ſhall make appear by and by. The <hi>Romans</hi> finding that it was a ſonorous letter, reject Υ as being a Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mute, and ſubſtitute for it <hi>n</hi> agreeing with it formally in that ſame analogy of ſound, but differing from it materially, as being formed by a diſtinct cloſure of Organs.</p>
            <p>Great <hi>Voſſius</hi> may excuſe my being ſo long upon this one letter: For he after ſpending a whole Chapter upon it, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes with a profeſt uncertainty of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whether to make it a ſingle letter, a <hi>Seſquilitera,</hi> or a double conſonant. I thought once I had been ſingular in my opinion about it; But afterwards meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with <hi>Doctor Wallis's</hi> Engliſh Grammar, I perceived that he had given the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of it long before me.</p>
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:57291:63"/>
            <p>The Semicloſe ſounds are of two ſorts, ſome of them are formed from the whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe ſounds and are called Aſpirats, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are formed by a partial open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Organs, and ſending forth the breath thro the mouth; hence the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them are ſix, <hi>f, th,</hi> Χ from <hi>p, t, k,</hi> and <hi>v, th</hi> (as in <hi>that) gh,</hi> from the Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutes <hi>b, d, g;</hi> for there can be no aſpirats from <hi>m, n, ng.</hi> 2. That nimble inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of articulate voice, the top of the Tongue brings forth three more ſemicloſe ſounds <hi>l, r, s,</hi> and ſo doubles the number of letters formed by the other organs. 1. L is formed by a cloſe appulſe of the top of the Tongue to the palat, the ſides not touching, but leaving an open paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, which diſtinguiſhes it from, <hi>n,</hi> where the appulſe makes a perfect cloſure. 2. The appulſe is from the ſides of the Tongue the top not touching, but leaving an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen paſſage to force out the breath; hence is formed the letter S. 3. A repeated or multiplyed appulſe of the tongue to the palat, by a quick motion of trepidation which produces R. S, has affinity to the cloſe mutes <hi>p, t, k,</hi> and therefore admits
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:57291:63" rendition="simple:additions"/>of being raiſed to a ſemimute, Z, both of which are capable of aſpiration, as the cloſe mutes and ſemimutes <hi>Sh, Zh.</hi> Theſe ſeem to me to be all the ſimple conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants in nature perfectly diſtinct, and to be made uſe of in a Philoſophical Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage for which this was firſt intended. And I think that this Analyſis of them from their Phyſical cauſes is plain &amp; eaſy, for to purſue all the minute differences of ſounds, as it were endleſs, ſo were it uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs.</p>
            <p>I come now to ſpeak of compounding two or more conſonants into one ſyllable, and that two waies, either in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or end of it; a thing well to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered by him who undertakes to frame a language by Art from the principles of Nature, and of no ſmall uſe in fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Grammar for Deaf perſons.</p>
            <p>That I may proceed the more diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this enquiry, I will begin with the definition of a Syllable, and paſſing by ſeveral other deſcript ons, I will keep to that of <hi>Priſcian</hi> and approved by <hi>Voſſius;</hi> as being moſt full and appoſite to my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. <hi>Syllaba eſt vox literalis, que ſub
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:57291:64"/>uno accentu, &amp; uno ſpiritu indiſtanter pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fertur.</hi> Where I ſuppoſe by <hi>ſub uno ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centu,</hi> and <hi>uno ſpiritu,</hi> there can be no more than one Vowel or Diphthong in a Syllable; which as a <hi>terminus communis</hi> unites the extreme conſonants on each ſide; Even as the <hi>copula</hi> units the Subject and the Predicate making one Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>My firſt Rule ſhall be: To ſpeak pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and in a ſtrict ſenſe, There can be no compoſition of Conſonants amongſt themſelves, either in the beginning or end of a Syllable, but what is preternatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and inconſiſtent with the definition of a Syllable. Who does not perceive, that even in the compoſition of Mutes and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quids in the beginning of a ſyllable as <hi>prat, plot,</hi> which of all compoſitions of conſonants is moſt common, and alſo judged moſt eaſy, as not making the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding Vowel long by poſition; yet I ſay even in thoſe it is eaſy to perceive a <hi>diſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia terminorum,</hi> and that they are united by a rapid ſpirit, as a <hi>terminus communis;</hi> and cannot poſſibly be otherwiſe, ſeeing they are formed by diſtinct cloſures of the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:57291:64"/>organs; and therefore there muſt be a <hi>Tranſitus</hi> from the one to the other; which appears yet much more evident in the end of a Syllable; with which kind of compoſition our Engliſh abounds very much as, <hi>Table, ridle, ſadle, little,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>It is true in ſome compoſitions of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonants the <hi>tranſitus</hi> not being from or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to organ, but from one degree of vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cality to another, as in <hi>lamp, hand, ink,</hi> the <hi>tranſitus</hi> here is ſo quick, that it may be ſaid to deceive the Ears; much like the colours of the Rainbow to the Eye, as it is in that ingenious deſcription of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rachnes</hi> Web. <hi>Ovid. Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Met.</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In quo diverſi niteant cum mille colores,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Tranſitus <hi>ipſe tamen ſpectantia lumina fallit:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> adeo quod tangit idem eſt; tamen ultima diſtant.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> But paſſing by the dictates of right rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Art, which certainly have not been followed in the primary Inſtitution of any language unleſs it be of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew alone; let us look to Uſe which is the Sovereign Lawgiver to all languages. And more particularly to the uſage of the Greek, which gives laws of Orthography to all the Occidental Languages: and
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:57291:65"/>firſt for the compounding of Conſonants in the beginning of a Syllable.</p>
            <p>Had the Grecians been as careleſs of Euphony and poliſhing their words in the terminations, as they have been in the initial Syllables, their language had been as much inferior to ſome others in Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phony, as now it is eſteemed more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and graceful. What more rude ſounds, uneaſy to be pronounced, and harſh to the Ear, than <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. What cauſe to aſcribe this to I am uncertain, whether to the rudeneſs of their language together with others, in its firſt origine; or to ſome modiſh affectation of times and humors, or more particularly to a Poetical humor of Syncopizing and contracting their words, which ſeems to me moſt probable. But this we ſee is certain, that they have taken to themſelves ſuch a liberty of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding Conſonants in the beginning of a Syllable, that their greateſt admirers the <hi>Romans</hi> have forſaken them in this; there ſcarce being any ſuch double con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonants, as any in the fore-mentioned
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:57291:65"/>examples in the beginning of a word, in all the Latin Tongue; unleſs it be in ſome few words, which are manifeſtly of a Greek origin. They have gone ſo far, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt no Rule can be formed for their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Syllables, but <hi>Quidlibet cum Quo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ibet.</hi> Howbeit will endeavor to reduce the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the Greek in this particular to ſome General Rules.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>There is no double conſonant to be found in the beginning of a Greek word, but one of them is a Lingual:</hi> theſe are, <hi>n, d, t, l, r, s, z, th, θ, sh, zh.</hi> Hence I obſerve that <hi>Voſſius</hi> goes too far, when he bids in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Greek to divide <hi>a-gmen, te-gmen;</hi> unleſs he could have produced authority for a ſhort vowel before this poſition, or a word beginning with <hi>gm,</hi> neither of which I think can be found.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The liquids (commonly ſo called) l, m, n, r, add, ng, never come before other conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, or one another in the beginning of a word,</hi> except <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>None of the cloſe Conſonants</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="116" facs="tcp:57291:66"/>
            <list>
               <item>Labials <hi>p, b, m,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Linguals <hi>t, d, n,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Gutturals. <hi>ng,</hi> r, <hi>k,</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Or their aſpirats.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Labials φ, <hi>v,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Linguals θ, <hi>th,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Gutturals. <hi>χ, gh,</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>If they be of the ſame Organ, can be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded with one another.</hi> Except <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. In theſe negatives the Latin, and I think other modern lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages do agree with them.</p>
            <p>For affirmative Rules the firſt ſhall be. <hi>The liquids L, R, come frequently after the Mutes and Semimutes, with their aſpirats</hi> as,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Rule is univerſally true <hi>de jure,</hi> tho not <hi>de facto;</hi> or, it is true <hi>de generibus ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulorum,</hi>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:57291:66"/>tho not <hi>de ſingulis generum.</hi> Hence tho there be no <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, yet analogy would bear it as well as <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> So in Latin, tho there be no words beginning with <hi>tl,</hi> yet <hi>tlarus</hi> would be as Analogical, as <hi>clarus</hi> or <hi>planus.</hi> So in Engliſh <hi>tlaſh</hi> were as Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonick as <hi>plaſh, claſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>S, in the beginning of a word comes before all kinds of Conſonants in that ſame Syllable;</hi> i. e. it is compounded with <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ſingulorum,</hi> tho not with <hi>Singula Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. For the Mutes <hi>p, t, k,</hi> and their a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats φ, θ χ, it is compounded with them all; as, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. 2. The Semimutes β, δ, <hi>r,</hi> it is only found with β, as <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and by the Dorick Dialect with δ, as <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. 3. Of the Sonorous or Naſales μ, <hi>r,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it is found only with μ, as <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>S.</hi> is not to be found before any of theſe three conſonants in Latin, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be in words taken from the Greek; and yet our Engliſh abounds with exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples both of <hi>ſm,</hi> and <hi>ſn,</hi> as <hi>ſmall, ſmooth, ſmite, ſnatch, ſnow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Except from the former Rule, its two ſiſter-ſemicloſe linguals, <hi>r, l,</hi> before which
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:57291:67"/>it never comes in Greek or Latin; Tho <hi>sl</hi> frequently in Engliſh, as <hi>ſleep, ſlow;</hi> and tho <hi>s</hi> it ſelf come not before <hi>r</hi> yet its aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <hi>sh</hi> is found with <hi>r</hi> as <hi>ſhrine, ſhrewd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>S</hi> in the beginning of a word comes after ſome both of the Mutes and Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutes, <hi>de facto,</hi> and therefore might come after them all <hi>eodem jure,</hi> ψ, Z, ξ, i. e. <hi>ps, ds, ks.</hi> Here it comes after two Mutes, <hi>k, p,</hi> and one Semimute, <hi>d.</hi> The reaſon in Nature were the ſame for <hi>bs, gs ts,</hi> in the beginning of a Syllable; but <hi>s</hi> after <hi>any</hi> other Conſonant in the beginning of a Syllable ſounds harſh, and layes a force upon nature. What could induce the Grecians to ſingle out theſe three double Conſonants ψ, Z, ξ, contracting them into one ſingle Character, and placing them in the Alphabet amongſt the ſimple Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of letters, is not eaſy to gueſs. Had they made a more ſoft and melting ſound than other double conſonants, this might have paſt for a tolerable Reaſon: But the caſe is quite contrary; for they make a ſtronger poſition after a ſhort vowel than many other donble conſonants do: or if frequency of uſe had been the induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:57291:67"/>this alſo had been tolerable; but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in this they muſt give place to many other double conſonants: unleſs perhaps it may be thought, that the frequency of ψ and ξ in the future tenſes of Verbs might have occaſioned this abbreviation. <hi>Voſſius</hi> gueſſes at the Origin of ψ, that it has been an imitation of the Hebrew צ. If he had made <hi>z</hi> and ξ to be of the ſame ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, his conjecture had been by much the more probable; for there is fully as great reaſon for theſe as for that. The affinity of ξ to צ is all one with ψ to צ; for both of them are compounded of <hi>S</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing a Mute. Again the affinity of z to צ is no leſs, for tho the one be mute, the other Semimute; yet they belong both to one organ of formation, which the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews take notice of as the greater affini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: So that if an imitation of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew may paſs for a probable reaſon of this Grammatication, it is much more likely, that a threefold abbreviation would induce them to this imitation, ſooner than a ſingle one; ſpecially conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that <hi>s</hi> never follows another con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant in compoſition in the beginning
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:57291:68"/>of a word, but in theſe three. I might add that the Hebrew Grammarians will ſcarce allow צ to be a double Conſonant, tho I dare not undertake to defend them in this.</p>
            <p>My next Rule ſhall be for trible Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants in the beginning of a word. 1. <hi>There can no word begin with three conſonants but where</hi> s <hi>is one.</hi> This is not only true in Greek and Latin, but I think alſo in our vulgar Europaean Languages. 2. <hi>S, never makes a triple conſonant in the beginning of a word, but with a mute and liquid follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> And this but rarely in Greek, as <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; ſo in Latin, as <hi>ſcrib<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſpretus, ſtratus;</hi> Tho the compoſition of <hi>s</hi> with any either ſingle or double conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in the beginning of a word, ſeems to be of no difficult pronounciation. And now I come to double and Triple conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants in the end of a Syllable.</p>
            <p>I think our Engliſh Tongue with its Mother Saxon, abounds more with this kind of cloſure or ending of words, with double and triple Conſonants, than any other common Language; which makes us cenſured by neighboring Nations, by comparing our pronounciation to the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:57291:68"/>barking of Dogs: For our words being for the moſt part Monoſyllables, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ending with a harſh colliſion of dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and trible conſonants, and admitting no Apoſtrophe; this makes us take the more time, and uſe the more force to ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The moſt natural and eaſy compoſition of Conſonants, either in the beginning or end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Syllable, is that of the Mutes and Semimutes, following the Sonorous letters of their own reſpective organs of formation;</hi> as in theſe examples.</p>
            <list>
               <item>mb <hi>Lamb, dumb, comb,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>mp <hi>lamp, imp, lump,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>nd <hi>hand, blind, round,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>nt <hi>Ant, hint, hunt,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>ngg <hi>thing, long, dung,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>ngk <hi>think, rank, drunk.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The compoſition of two conſonants next for facility to the former, is when the three ſemicloſe linguals, l, r, s, come before other conſonants in the end of a ſyllable.</hi> Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in Engliſh are obvious: It is true, not of theſe three coming before <hi>all</hi> other letters; yet the reaſon is the ſame for all, tho uſe be not.</p>
            <pb n="122" facs="tcp:57291:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>S in the end of a word, according to the uſe of our Engliſh, makes a double conſonant after any other letter, unleſs it be after q, z.</hi> Other double conſonants there are in the end of a word; but being very ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular and of a harſh ſound. I paſs them by; ſuch, as, <hi>ſoft, length, right, apt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>For trible Conſonants in the end of a ſyllable there is none found in any language but where S makes one.</hi> I know the <hi>Dutch</hi> write <hi>Handt,</hi> but I ſuppoſe they muſt pronounce either <hi>hand</hi> or <hi>hant;</hi> for a mute and ſemimute of that ſame organ are inconſiſtent ſounds. And as for our <hi>ſtrength,</hi> and <hi>length;</hi> 1. Tho they be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with four conſonants; yet we ſound but two neither of which can be written in Engliſh, but with two Characters; But 2ly, I think the moſt genuin pronouncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe two words is, as if they were written <hi>ſtrenth</hi> and <hi>lenth</hi> according to the Northern Dialect.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>And laſtly, allowing two ss in two di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct places</hi> (which often happens) <hi>there may be, and are</hi> de facto, <hi>in Engliſh four conſonants after a Vowel in that ſame ſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> as in <hi>firſts, thirſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:57291:69"/>
            <p>This doctrine of double and trible con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonants, ſo far as concerns the ending of words, has but little place in the learned languages; yet examples are found both in Greek and Latin, even of Trible con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonants; as <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſtirps.</hi> Where obſerve that there are no words in Greek ending either in double or trible conſonants, but where <hi>s</hi> either virtually or expreſsly is the laſt; and but very few in Latin ending in other double Conſonants; Some in <hi>nt</hi> as <hi>amant ſunt,</hi> ſome few in <hi>nc,</hi> as <hi>hinc hunc,</hi> in <hi>st,</hi> as <hi>eſt poſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My laſt enquiry about double Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants ſhall be. How many may come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in one ſyllable? To which I anſwer. Firſt, If we follow reaſon &amp; the Authority of the ancienteſt language, there can come no more than two, one before and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther after the vowel. 2ly If we follow the uſage of the other two learned languages Greek and Latin; ſecluding the letter <hi>s,</hi> there can be no ſyllable of above four conſonants, two before, and two after the Vowel. 3ly Admitting <hi>s,</hi> which comes both before and after moſt letters, there may be a ſyllable of ſix conſonants, three
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:57291:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>before and three after the vowel. I grant there is no example found either in Latin or Greek of above five conſonants; yet there are many examples in both of three conſonants in the beginning, as <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo;</hi> ſo of three in the end, as <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſtirps,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is above this, is harſh and Barbarous.</p>
            <p>I have heard learned men of the Poliſh Nation affirm, that there is a Monoſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable of nine letters in that Language, the Orthography of which I took from the hand of a perſon of Honor of that Nation, thus <hi>Chrzaszcz,</hi> This word I have often heard pronounced by Natives, and have my ſelf been commended by them for my imitation: But to ſtrangers it ſeems a barbarous ſound, and reaches not the expreſſing of the power of all the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with which it is written. <hi>Voſſius</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms as much of the <hi>Dutch.</hi> The word he inſtances in is, <hi>t'strengſt.</hi> But I am ſure if this be allowed for a Monoſyllable, there may be a monoſyllable of eleven letters, according to the Analogy both of the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Engliſh;</hi> or rather I may ſay, that there can be no bounds ſet to the Tongue in this particular. For firſt
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:57291:70"/>if <hi>t'strengſt,</hi> why not <hi>st'strengſt;</hi> for it is clear even from the ſame inſtance, that <hi>s</hi> may come before <hi>t</hi> in that ſame ſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. If it be ſaid that the letter <hi>s</hi> cannot be repeated thrice, in diſtinct places of that ſame ſyllable. Firſt, I anſwer by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torting; much leſs can <hi>t</hi> be repeated thrice, as here; for laying this one word aſide, I think it will be hard either to prove by reaſon, or to bring another in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance out of any language whatever, where a word conſiſting of three <hi>ttt</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned from one another by the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of other letters is eſteemed a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſyllable. 2ly The Analogy of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh allows of ſuch a Monoſyllable, as <hi>Spaſms, Schiſms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again if <hi>stſtrengſt</hi> why not <hi>ſtſtrengſts,</hi> and ſo <hi>in infinitum.</hi> That <hi>s</hi> after <hi>t</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent in the end of a ſyllable, our Engliſh abounds with Examples, as <hi>Taſts, faſts.</hi> But here it is obſervable that this compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition we admit of, <hi>s</hi> coming both before and after another Conſonant in the end of a ſyllable, is very harſh and uneaſy, and ſcarce to be found in any other language. The <hi>French</hi> make many ſhifts to avoid
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:57291:71"/>the harſhneſs of <hi>s</hi> either before or after another conſonant, and chiefly in the end of a ſyllable: if <hi>s</hi> go before, they leave it out, as in <hi>haſte, viſte;</hi> if it come after they leave out the conſonant that goes before it; as in <hi>loups, animaux.</hi> Another thing obſervable of <hi>s</hi> with its affinis <hi>l;</hi> when they come alone without the implication of other conſonants: they are of an eaſy and graceful pronounciation. <hi>Homer</hi> ſeems to have loved them, as in theſe,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>—</l>
                  <l>—<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>That the Preſs ſhould have ſtript theſe broken ends of Verſes of the unneceſſary and troubleſome luggage of Spirits and Accents, is neither the Compoſitor nor the Correctors fault: I am obliged to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them and take the fault, if there be any, upon my ſelf; or rather lay it over upon the Author; who were he alive, he would excuſe both me and himſelf, by the Uſe of the times he lived in: And <hi>uſe</hi> we know is the ſupreme Law in all languages. But if all this do not ſatisfy the Critical Helleniſt; Then I muſt add further, that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> in the preſent caſe, will even dare to
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:57291:71"/>appeal to right Reaſon: For what ever may be ſaid for the cumberſome tackling of Spirits and Accents in Proſe; yet in a Verſe, Accents are down-right non-ſenſe, unleſs it be <hi>tollendae ambiguitatis cauſa</hi> in aequivocal words.</p>
            <p>That all other Appendages beſide the letters are unneceſſary and troubleſome, I ſhall inſtance only in one word, which is ſo overgrown with the Rickets, that the Head is much greater than the whole Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; for whereas the letters of the word are but three, the other appurtenances of it are five: And had it all that ſwelling furniture about it in the Gloſſology, which it hath in the Typology, it would choke one to pronounce it. But he muſt have more critical Ears than mine, that can perceive five diſtinctions in <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which are not to be heard in our Engliſh ERR. That this is not a word either made or ſought by me, appears by this paſſage of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Epigram.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>And here I ſhall take the liberty to go one ſtep further out of my road, by taking
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:57291:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>notice that the Grecians have laſht out a little too far, in that which is thought to be the greateſt grace of their language: That is, <hi>their words ending much in Vowels and Diphthongs; and theſe frequently mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> pure <hi>ſyllables, one, two, or more, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the intervention of a Conſonant.</hi> One, two, or at leaſt three, one would think were enough for Euphony; but four, five, or ſometimes ſix in the end of a word, I think is too much; ſpecially, if they make ſo many ſyllables, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſounds well; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is yet more ſoft and melting; and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſounds high and lofty from the mouth of a Poet, and Symbolizeth with the more Symbolical Hemiſtich pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding it.</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <p>But <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and by a Dialyſis <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is too ſoft and luſhious. And for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I know not what other cenſure to paſs on them, but that they are childiſh and ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Trauliſms. It is true that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Typology of the word, has its Sylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles diſtinct enough; but the beſt can be ſaid of it will leave them too identical in the Gloſſology. Again for <hi>Ae Ae Ae,</hi> which
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:57291:72"/>is the word of the greateſt number of vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els without a Conſonant, that I have hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to meet with; tho it be manifeſtly of a Greek origin, yet I know not where to father it upon any Greek Author, <hi>toti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem literis &amp; ſyllabis:</hi> which makes me ſtrange the more to ſee the grave and Manly <hi>Roman,</hi> who in his imitation of the effeminate <hi>Greculus,</hi> hath with a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful judgment, ſhall I ſay or happineſs, equally avoided the extremes of too much harſhneſs in the beginning of his words, and too much ſoftneſs and delicacy in the end of them; yet in this one word to have outdone him in number of vowels, tho not of ſyllables. <hi>Ovid,</hi> is my Author for this. <hi>Metamorph. lib.</hi> 4.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Nec tenet Ae Ae Ae genetrix pulcherrima Circes.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>But to return from this digreſſion to another obſervation upon the letters, L, and S. Theſe two letters ſeem to me to make a great impreſſion upon the body of the French Tongue (as the particles and chiefly the pronouns do in all languages) becauſe of their ſo frequent uſe in the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocabula</hi> of that language. I have often been pleaſantly affected to hear two talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:57291:73"/>
               <hi>French,</hi> when the pronominal words recurred often; ſuch as, <hi>ce, cett, c'eſt cettui, cettuici, cettuila, lui, celui, icelui, elle, icelle, celleci, cellece,</hi> &amp;c. and many ſuch like de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending from the fruitful ſtock of <hi>ca &amp; la:</hi> for theſe words comming from a French mouth, make a pretty ſoft whiſpering noiſe affecting the Ear pleaſantly. Our own Engliſh pronominal words are none of the moſt graceful pronounciation, chiefly becauſe of the ſo frequent uſe of <hi>th</hi> as <hi>thou, thy, that, the, this, thoſe, their,</hi> &amp;c. This makes Outlandiſh men call us <hi>blaeſi,</hi> the ſound of <hi>th</hi> never being heard a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, but by liſpers; who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce <hi>s</hi> vitiouſly by the power of this letter. I will conclude with rectifying an Univerſal miſtake of all that have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of Grammar, for want of conſidering the Nature of double conſonants. It has paſt for currant amongſt all Grammari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that we are to divide words in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Languages, following the uſe of double Conſonants among the Grecians; as, <hi>ma-gnus, do-ctus, le-ctus, a-ptus,</hi> and not <hi>mag-nus, doc-tus, lec-tus, ap-tus,</hi> Voſſius goes yet further (as I have had occaſion to
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:57291:73"/>mention before) and bids us divide <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gmen a-gmen;</hi> tho their be no precedent for this in Greek. One Ancient Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marian goes yet a ſtep further, and bids follow this Rule even in compounded words; as <hi>o-bruo, o-bligo,</hi> which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding others do except. But <hi>Priſcian</hi> does well refute this Authors opinion by this argument, That Poets never uſed theſe ſyllables ſhort: So that for the very ſame reaſon, we muſt not divide <hi>le-ctus, do-ctus,</hi> becauſe they are uſed ſtil long by poſition.</p>
            <p>Tho this reaſon be convincing enough; yet there is another reaſon worthy to be mentioned in this place, which alſo illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and confirms what I have ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: that the primitive words of other languages (excepting the Hebrew) are for the moſt part Monoſyllables. In all primitive words I diſtinguiſh between ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical and ſervile letters: the radical part of the word generally both in Greek and Latin is effable in one ſyllable, <hi>amo, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceo; am</hi> and <hi>doc</hi> are the radical letters, <hi>o</hi> in the one and <hi>eo</hi> in the other being ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viles; and ſo changeable in the oblique
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:57291:74"/>inflexion of the words, therefore I think it were reaſonable in dividing the word to diſtinguiſh between what is radical, and what is ſervile.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="afterword">
            <head>Poſt-Script.</head>
            <p>Tho I make no queſtion, but I have ſaid as much as may enable any perſon of ordinary capacity, with extraordinary diligence, to become if not a Didaſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locophus, at leaſt a Hypodidaſcalus to ſome more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert Maſter; yet my main deſign being not ſo much to make every Grammaticaſter a Didaſcalocophus, as to ſatisfy learned men, that Cophology is none, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; This has made me the shorter in the practical part. So that any pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitioner in this Art, not more Maſter of it than my ſelf, muſt be beholding to me for ſome more particular directions. Wherefore if any Philocophus should challenge my ſelf, to make good the Title of my book: let him bring a Subject ducly qualified, male or female, the younger the better; and he shall find me ready to anſwer his challenge, either perſonally or by proxy.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
